<section anchor="introduction" numbered="true">
  <name>Introduction</name>
  <t>
    Autonomous AI agents are deployed in production environments to act
    on behalf of human and organisational principals. An agent may send
    emails, book appointments, make purchases, access file systems, spawn
    child agents to complete subtasks, and communicate across multiple
    platforms, all without explicit human approval for each action.
  </t>
  <t>
    This creates an identity gap. When an agent presents itself to an
    API, a payment processor, or another agent, there is no standard
    mechanism to establish: the agent's persistent identity across
    interactions; the human or organisation on whose authority it acts;
    the specific actions it is permitted to take; whether it has been
    compromised or revoked; or whether it has a trustworthy history.
  </t>
  <t>
    AIP addresses this gap. It is designed as neutral, open
    infrastructure analogous to HTTP, OAuth, and JWT, providing
    infrastructure that any application can build on without vendor
    dependency.
  </t>

  <section anchor="motivation" numbered="true">
    <name>Motivation</name>
    <t>
      The absence of an identity standard creates concrete operational
      problems. Services cannot implement fine-grained agent access
      control. Humans have no auditable record of what their agents did.
      Compromised agents cannot be reliably stopped. Agent-to-agent
      systems have no basis for trust.
    </t>
    <t>
      Existing deployments typically operate in one of two modes: no
      access, or full access. AIP introduces fine-grained capability
      declarations. A principal can grant <tt>email.read</tt> without
      <tt>email.send</tt>, or <tt>transactions</tt> with a
      <tt>max_daily_total</tt> constraint.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="design-philosophy" numbered="true">
    <name>Design Philosophy</name>
    <t>
      AIP is built on five design principles:
    </t>
    <t>
      Neutral and open. The spec is released under CC0 and the
      <tt>did:aip</tt> DID method is registered with the W3C.
    </t>
    <t>
      Build on existing standards. AIP builds on W3C DID, JWT
      <xref target="RFC7519"/>, JWK <xref target="RFC7517"/>, DPoP
      <xref target="RFC9449"/>, and CRL patterns from
      <xref target="RFC5280"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      Human sovereignty. Every agent action must trace to a human or
      authorised organisational principal.
    </t>
    <t>
      Security proportional to risk. AIP defines three security tiers
      matching overhead to risk level.
    </t>
    <t>
      Deterministic verification. The Validation Algorithm (Section 7.2) is fully
      deterministic: two independent implementations executing the same
      steps on the same token will reach the same result.
    </t>
    <t>
      Zero Trust Architecture. AIP implements the zero trust principles
      defined in <xref target="SP-800-207"/> and satisfies NIST SP 800-63-4
      <xref target="SP-800-63-4"/> AAL2 for agent-to-service interactions.
      No agent is implicitly trusted by virtue of its origin, network
      location, or prior successful interaction. Every Credential Token
      must be validated against the Registry on every interaction.
      Short-lived Credential Tokens bound by a mandatory TTL
      limit the blast radius of any credential compromise. Revocation is
      checked in real time for Tier 2 sensitive operations (Section 17.3).
      DPoP proof-of-possession (Section 17.3) ensures that possession of a
      valid Credential Token is insufficient for impersonation without the
      corresponding private key material, satisfying the anti-replay
      requirement of <xref target="SP-800-207"/> Section 3.
    </t>
    <t>
      Integration with Model Context Protocol (MCP). AIP provides the
      agent identity, authorization, and delegation layer that MCP server
      implementations require but do not define. An AIP-authenticated
      agent can obtain scoped access tokens for MCP servers via the token
      exchange mechanism defined in Section 7.1.4. AIP does not replace MCP;
      it provides the identity substrate on which MCP authorization
      decisions are made. See Section 7.1.4 (Token Exchange) and Section 15.5
      (OAuth Authorization Server) for the concrete integration path.
    </t>
    <t>
      Least Privilege. Agents are granted only the specific capabilities
      required for their declared purpose, expressed as signed Capability
      Manifests (Section 4.2.3). Capability grants are always additive from
      principal to agent and never exceed the granting principal's own
      capability set. A child agent must not be granted capabilities that
      the delegating parent does not itself hold (Rule D-1, Section 4.2.10).
      The max_delegation_depth field (Section 8) bounds the depth of
      sub-agent hierarchies, limiting transitive capability propagation.
      Capability constraints allow fine-grained least-privilege expression
      within each capability category, consistent with
      <xref target="SP-800-207"/> Section 3 (Tenets 5 and 6).
    </t>
    <t>
      Relationship to SPIFFE/SPIRE. SPIFFE is designed for workload
      identity within enumerable, infrastructure-managed environments. AIP
      is designed for autonomous agents that are created dynamically,
      operate across organisational boundaries, and act on behalf of named
      human principals whose authority must be cryptographically
      traceable. An enterprise may deploy SPIFFE for its internal service
      mesh and AIP for its agent fleet without conflict. The two
      mechanisms are complementary and operate at distinct layers of the
      identity stack.
    </t>
    <t>
      Relationship to MCP. The Model Context Protocol <xref target="MCP"/>
      defines how AI agents discover and invoke tools and data sources.
      AIP is the agent identity layer that sits beneath MCP's
      authorisation flow: AIP establishes that an agent is who it claims
      to be (identification via Credential Token), that it was authorised
      by a named human principal (delegation chain in the Principal
      Token), and that it holds specific capabilities (Capability
      Manifest). AIP does not replace MCP's tool-access OAuth flow - it
      provides the agent identity that OAuth's "sub" claim cannot supply
      when the subject is an autonomous agent rather than a human user.
    </t>
    <t>
      Out of scope - Prompt injection prevention. AIP is an identity and
      authorisation protocol. Whether the content an agent processes
      contains adversarial instructions is an application-layer and
      model-layer concern outside this specification's scope. AIP
      mitigates the persistence window of a successful prompt injection
      attack: a compromised agent may be immediately revoked via
      <tt>full_revoke</tt> (Section 9.1), and revocation propagates to all
      child agents within the TTL window defined in Section 7.1.2. AIP does
      not prevent the initial injection - it limits the attacker's
      persistence.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="architecture-layers" numbered="true">
    <name>Architecture Layers</name>
    <t>
      AIP is structured as six ordered layers:
    </t>
    <figure anchor="aip-architecture-layers">
      <name>AIP Architecture Layers</name>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
 +------------------------------------------------------+
 | Layer 6 - Reputation Trust over time                 |
 +------------------------------------------------------+
 | Layer 5 - Revocation Standard kill switch            |
 +------------------------------------------------------+
 | Layer 4 - Credential Token & Verification            |
 |           Cryptographic proof                        |
 +------------------------------------------------------+
 | Layer 3 - Capabilities What the agent can do         |
 +------------------------------------------------------+
 | Layer 2 - Principal Chain Who authorised it          |
 |           incl. AIP-GRANT and Approval Envelopes     |
 +------------------------------------------------------+
 | Layer 1 - Core Identity Who the agent IS             |
 +------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
    </figure>
  </section>
</section>
