<section anchor="conventions" numbered="true">
  <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
  <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
    "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
    BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and
    only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
  </t>
  <t>
    This document uses "MUST" in preference to "SHALL" throughout for
    consistency. Where earlier drafts used "SHALL", the normative force
    is identical; the term has been normalised to "MUST" per this
    convention.
  </t>
  <t>
    JSON is used throughout this document as defined in
    <xref target="RFC8259"/>. URIs are used as defined in
    <xref target="RFC3986"/>. ABNF notation is used as defined in
    <xref target="RFC5234"/>, including its core rules (ALPHA, DIGIT,
    HEXDIG, SP, etc.) as defined in RFC5234 Appendix B.1. HTTP status
    codes, headers, and semantics are as defined in <xref target="RFC9110"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
    All Ed25519 signatures are computed per <xref target="RFC8032"/>.
    DPoP proofs are constructed per <xref target="RFC9449"/>.
  </t>

  <section anchor="canonical-serialization" numbered="true">
    <name>Canonical JSON Serialization</name>
    <t>
      Several objects in this specification are signed outside the JWT
      framework. For those objects, the following canonical JSON
      serialization procedure MUST be used when computing or verifying
      signatures, and when computing Action Hashes:
    </t>
    <ol type="%d">
      <li>Represent the object as a JSON value per <xref target="RFC8259"/>.</li>
      <li>Recursively sort all object keys in lexicographic ascending order
      (Unicode code point order). Array element order MUST be preserved;
      arrays MUST NOT be sorted.</li>
      <li>Remove all insignificant whitespace (no spaces, tabs, or
      newlines outside string values).</li>
      <li>Encode the result as a UTF-8 byte sequence with no BOM.</li>
      <li>Before computing any signature, set the object's
      <tt>"signature"</tt> field to the empty string <tt>""</tt>. The
      <tt>"signature"</tt> field MUST be included in the serialisation at
      its lexicographically correct position with value <tt>""</tt>.</li>
    </ol>
    <t>
      This procedure is equivalent to the JSON Canonicalization Scheme
      (JCS) defined in <xref target="RFC8785"/>. Implementations SHOULD use
      an RFC8785-conformant library to ensure correctness. When this
      procedure is used to compute Action Hashes,
      implementations MUST use an RFC8785-conformant library; custom
      serializer implementations MUST NOT be used for that purpose.
    </t>
    <t>EXAMPLE (informative):</t>
    <sourcecode><![CDATA[
 {"z": 1, "a": 2, "m": [3,1,2]}  →  {"a":2,"m":[3,1,2],"z":1}
]]></sourcecode>
    <t>
      NOTE: This canonical serialization applies to Capability Manifests,
      Agent Identity Objects, Revocation Objects, Endorsement Objects,
      GrantRequest Objects (when signed), and Approval Envelopes. It does
      NOT apply to JWT-format objects (Credential Tokens, Principal
      Tokens), which use standard JWS compact serialization per
      <xref target="RFC7515"/>.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
