<section anchor="terminology" numbered="true">
  <name>Definitions and Terminology</name>
  <t>
    The following terms are used throughout this specification:
  </t>

  <dl newline="false">
    <dt>Agent:</dt>
    <dd>An autonomous software system powered by a large language model
      that can perceive inputs, reason about them, and execute actions
      in the world on behalf of a principal.</dd>

    <dt>Agent Identity Descriptor (AID):</dt>
    <dd><t>A cryptographically derived, persistent identifier for an agent
      conforming to the did:aip DID method defined in Section 4.1. An AID is
      a W3C DID. A standalone <tt>did:aip</tt> string does not encode its
      authoritative Registry; resolution requires Registry context as defined
      in Section 7.</t></dd>

    <dt>Decentralized Identifier (DID):</dt>
    <dd>A W3C Decentralized Identifier. DID Documents, DID URLs, and DID
      resolution are used as defined by W3C DID Core.</dd>

    <dt>Production Deployment:</dt>
    <dd>Any AIP Registry or Relying Party deployment where more than one
      process, container, or server instance may validate tokens for the same
      AID simultaneously, or where the deployment serves external principals
      not under the operator's direct control. Deployments that are explicitly
      single-instance and serve only internal development or testing purposes
      are not production deployments for the purposes of
      <xref target="token-cache-requirements-stateless"/>.</dd>

    <dt>Principal:</dt>
    <dd><t>The human or organisational entity on whose authority an agent
      acts. Every AIP delegation chain MUST have a verifiable principal
      at its root. Principals are identified by W3C DIDs, but NOT by did:aip (which is reserved for agents).</t></dd>

    <dt>Agent Deployer:</dt>
    <dd>The party that provisions an agent on behalf of a principal.
      May be the principal themselves or a service acting with the
      principal's explicit consent.</dd>

    <dt>Principal Wallet:</dt>
    <dd>Software that holds the principal's DID private key and
      implements the AIP-GRANT consent and signing ceremony.
      Throughout this document, Principal Wallet references use this capitalized
      term unless the context explicitly describes a generic wallet ecosystem.</dd>

    <dt>Capability Manifest:</dt>
    <dd>A versioned, signed JSON document stored in the Registry that
      declares the specific permissions (scopes and constraints) granted
      to an agent. Defined in Section 5.3.</dd>

    <dt>Credential Token:</dt>
    <dd>A signed JWT-format token presented by an agent to a Relying
      Party as proof of identity and authorisation for a specific
      interaction. Defined in Section 8.1.</dd>

    <dt>Step Execution Token (SET):</dt>
    <dd>A short-lived Registry-issued JWT, distinct from an agent-issued
      Credential Token, attesting that a specific Approval Envelope step has
      been claimed by its designated actor. Defined in Section 13.8 and
      validated using the Step Execution Token profile in Section 9.</dd>

    <dt>Principal Token:</dt>
    <dd><t>A signed JWT payload encoding one delegation link in the AIP
      principal chain. Principal Tokens are embedded as compact-serialised
      JWTs in the aip_chain array of a Credential Token or Step Execution
      Token.
      Defined in Section 5.5.</t></dd>

    <dt>Relying Party (RP):</dt>
    <dd>Any service, API, or agent that receives and verifies an AIP
      Credential Token or Step Execution Token. Responsible for implementing
      the Validation Algorithm (Section 9).</dd>

    <dt>Authorization Server (AS):</dt>
    <dd>The OAuth 2.1 authorization server role. In G3 grant flows, the
      Registry commonly acts as the AS for authorization-code and token
      endpoints.</dd>

    <dt>Delegation:</dt>
    <dd>The act of granting a subset of capabilities from a principal or
      parent agent to a child agent. Formally expressed as a Principal
      Token in the delegation chain.</dd>

    <dt>Delegation Depth:</dt>
    <dd>A non-negative integer counter incremented at each delegation
      step. An agent directly authorised by the root principal has
      delegation depth 0. A child agent of that agent has delegation
      depth 1, and so on.</dd>

    <dt>Tier:</dt>
    <dd>An operation security classification derived from the highest-risk
      requested scope in the synced AIP Scope Catalog. Tier determines the
      applicable revocation-checking mode, maximum Credential Token lifetime,
      and mandatory security mechanisms. Three Tiers are defined in
      <xref target="architecture-tiers"/>. Tier selection on performance or
      availability grounds alone, without using the synced catalog metadata,
      is a misconfiguration and a violation of AIP's zero-trust model.</dd>

    <dt>Grant Tier:</dt>
    <dd>One of three standardised AIP-GRANT ceremony profiles: G1
      (Registry-Mediated), G2 (Direct Deployer), G3 (Full Ceremony).
      Defined in Section 12. Grant Tier is a ceremony-assurance axis; it is
      distinct from the security Tier derived from an operation's requested
      scopes.</dd>

    <dt>Capability Overlay:</dt>
    <dd>A Registry-stored, issuer-signed document that restricts an
      agent's effective capability set for a specific engagement or issuer
      context. Defined in Section 5.11.</dd>

    <dt>Engagement Object:</dt>
    <dd>A mutable Registry resource that models a multi-party engagement,
      serving as the parent container for Capability Overlays, Approval
      Envelopes, and participant rosters. Defined in Section 5.12.</dd>

    <dt>Approval Envelope:</dt>
    <dd>A signed document submitted to the Registry that pre-authorises a
      complete multi-step workflow in a single principal signing ceremony.
      Decouples approval from execution. Defined in Section 13.</dd>

    <dt>Action Hash:</dt>
    <dd>A SHA-256 hash of the canonical JSON representation of an approval
      step's action descriptor. Binds approval to a specific operation.
      Computed per Section 13.7.</dd>

    <dt>Registry:</dt>
    <dd>The authoritative store and resolver for AIP agents, Capability
      Manifests, revocation state, and delegation chains. Implements the
      Registry Interface (<xref target="registry"/>) and the Validation
      Algorithm (<xref target="credential-token-validation"/>). May be operated by a principal, a service, or a
      consortium.</dd>

    <dt>AIP-GRANT:</dt>
    <dd>The principal authorization protocol defining how principals
      authorize agents through a consent ceremony. Defined in Section
      12.</dd>

    <dt>Revocation Object:</dt>
    <dd>A signed document declaring that an agent's grant is revoked,
      either in whole (<tt>full_revoke</tt>) or in part (<tt>scope_revoke</tt>
      or <tt>delegation_revoke</tt>). Defined in Section 5.7.</dd>

    <dt>Certificate Revocation List (CRL):</dt>
    <dd>An AIP signed JSON revocation artifact published by the Registry for
      Tier 1 bounded-staleness validation. Tier 2 and Tier 3 validation use
      live Registry revocation status lookups; they do not satisfy their
      real-time revocation requirement by fetching an on-demand CRL. Defined
      in <xref target="crl"/>.</dd>

    <dt>DPoP Proof:</dt>
    <dd>A Demonstration of Proof-of-Possession as defined in <xref
      target="RFC9449"/>. Mandatory for Tier 2 and Tier 3 operations, and
      also mandatory for any Tier 1 scope or endpoint that explicitly
      requires DPoP. Binds a Credential Token to a specific HTTP request and
      the agent's key material.</dd>

    <dt>Authentication Assurance Level 2 (AAL2):</dt>
    <dd>A NIST SP 800-63 assurance level for authentication strength. When
      this specification refers to AAL2, it means AAL2 as defined by the
      cited NIST SP 800-63 document.</dd>

    <dt>JWK, JWS, and JWT:</dt>
    <dd>JSON Web Key, JSON Web Signature, and JSON Web Token, respectively.
      AIP uses JWK for public key representation, JWS compact serialization
      for signed JWTs, and JWT payloads for Credential Tokens, Principal
      Tokens, Step Execution Tokens, and RPNP push notifications.</dd>

    <dt>Lowercase Hexadecimal Encoding (LCHEX):</dt>
    <dd>The lowercase hexadecimal representation of a byte string, using
      characters <tt>0-9</tt> and <tt>a-f</tt> only.</dd>

    <dt>Registry Push Notification Protocol (RPNP):</dt>
    <dd>The optional Registry push protocol for revocation notifications,
      defined in <xref target="rpnp"/>.</dd>

    <dt>Enterprise Identity Provider (Enterprise IdP):</dt>
    <dd>An OAuth 2.0/2.1 or OIDC-compliant authorization server operated by
      an enterprise organisation, such as Microsoft Entra ID, Okta, Ping
      Identity, or an equivalent system, that manages human principal
      identities, enforces enterprise access policies including Conditional
      Access and ABAC, and issues access tokens scoped to enterprise
      resources. In AIP, an Enterprise IdP is the authorization server that a
      Relying Party trusts for resource access tokens, distinct from the AIP
      Registry acting as an OAuth AS for AIP-scope token exchange. Registries
      identify an Enterprise IdP by the presence of the
      <tt>enterprise_idp_required</tt> flag on a registered resource record
      (see <xref target="enterprise-idp-federation-profile"/>).</dd>

    <dt>Endorsement:</dt>
    <dd>A signed statement affirming a positive experience or outcome of
      an interaction with an agent. Contributes to the agent's reputation
      score. Defined in Section 14.1.</dd>
  </dl>

  <section anchor="abbreviations" numbered="true">
    <name>Abbreviations</name>
    <t>
      The following common abbreviations are used with their ordinary industry
      meanings or with the referenced external specifications:
    </t>
    <dl newline="false">
      <dt>ABAC</dt><dd>Attribute-Based Access Control.</dd>
      <dt>BOM</dt><dd>Byte Order Mark. AIP canonical JSON signing input uses
        UTF-8 without a leading BOM.</dd>
      <dt>CDN</dt><dd>Content Delivery Network.</dd>
      <dt>DAG</dt><dd>Directed Acyclic Graph.</dd>
      <dt>FIDO2/WebAuthn</dt><dd>FIDO2 and Web Authentication.</dd>
      <dt>HSM</dt><dd>Hardware Security Module.</dd>
      <dt>HMAC</dt><dd>Hash-based Message Authentication Code.</dd>
      <dt>JCS</dt><dd>JSON Canonicalization Scheme, defined by <xref target="RFC8785"/>.</dd>
      <dt>JWKS</dt><dd>JSON Web Key Set, the JWK container format used by
        OAuth and OIDC providers to publish signing keys.</dd>
      <dt>MITM</dt><dd>Man-in-the-Middle.</dd>
      <dt>mTLS</dt><dd>Mutual TLS.</dd>
      <dt>OCSP</dt><dd>Online Certificate Status Protocol, defined by <xref target="RFC6960"/>.</dd>
      <dt>PII</dt><dd>Personally Identifiable Information.</dd>
      <dt>PKCE</dt><dd>Proof Key for Code Exchange, defined by <xref target="RFC7636"/>.</dd>
      <dt>SAGA</dt><dd>Distributed-workflow compensation pattern.</dd>
      <dt>SLA</dt><dd>Service-Level Agreement.</dd>
      <dt>TTL</dt><dd>Time To Live.</dd>
    </dl>
  </section>

  <section anchor="architecture-tiers" numbered="true">
    <name>Architecture Tiers</name>
    <t>
      AIP defines three security Tiers that map synced AIP Scope Catalog
      metadata to mandatory protocol behaviors. Tiers are NOT performance
      classes and are not locally chosen labels; they are derived from the
      highest-risk requested scope.
    </t>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Tier 1 (Bounded-staleness):</strong> Optimized for high availability
        and low latency. Revocation is checked against a Registry-published CRL
        with a mandatory 15-minute update SLA. Principals MAY use <tt>did:key</tt>
        for Tier 1 operations.</li>
      <li><strong>Tier 2 (Real-time):</strong> The default Tier for sensitive operations.
        Revocation status MUST be checked in real-time against the Registry on
        every interaction. DPoP proof-of-possession (RFC 9449) is REQUIRED.
        Principals MUST use <tt>did:web</tt> to enable Registry trust anchoring.</li>
      <li><strong>Tier 3 (Regulated/Enterprise):</strong> The highest security level
        for regulated or high-value environments. Tier 3 supplements Tier 2 with
        mandatory mutual TLS (mTLS) and certificate revocation checking using
        OCSP or an equivalent deployment-profile mechanism defined in
        Section 21.6.</li>
    </ul>
    <t>
      The complete mapping of Tiers to normative protocol requirements is defined in
      the Tier Conformance Table in Section 20.1.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
