<section anchor="credential-tokens" numbered="true">
  <name>Credential Tokens</name>

  <section anchor="token-structure" numbered="true">
    <name>Token Structure</name>
    <t>
      An AIP Credential Token is transmitted as an HTTP Authorization
      header:
    </t>
    <t>EXAMPLE (informative):</t>
    <sourcecode><![CDATA[
 Authorization: AIP <token>
 X-AIP-Version: 0.3
]]></sourcecode>
    <t>
      For interactions requiring Proof-of-Possession:
    </t>
    <t>EXAMPLE (informative):</t>
    <sourcecode><![CDATA[
 Authorization: AIP <token>
 DPoP: <dpop-proof>
 X-AIP-Version: 0.3
]]></sourcecode>
    <t>
      The <tt>X-AIP-Version</tt> HTTP header MUST carry the full protocol
      version string, identical to the <tt>aip_version</tt> JWT claim
     . For this specification, the value MUST be
      <tt>"0.3"</tt>. Implementations MUST reject requests where the
      <tt>X-AIP-Version</tt> header carries a version value that does not
      match a supported <tt>aip_version</tt>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="token-issuance" numbered="true">
    <name>Token Issuance</name>
    <t>
      Implementations MUST enforce the following maximum token lifetimes:
    </t>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr><th>Scope Category</th><th>Maximum TTL</th></tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr><td>All standard scopes (<tt>email.*</tt>, <tt>calendar.*</tt>, <tt>web.*</tt>, etc.)</td><td>3600 seconds (1 hour)</td></tr>
        <tr><td><tt>transactions.*</tt> or <tt>communicate.*</tt></td><td>300 seconds (5 minutes)</td></tr>
        <tr><td><tt>filesystem.execute</tt></td><td>300 seconds (5 minutes)</td></tr>
        <tr><td><tt>spawn_agents.create</tt> or <tt>spawn_agents.manage</tt></td><td>300 seconds (5 minutes)</td></tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <t>
      When a token contains scopes from multiple categories, the most
      restrictive TTL applies. Zero-duration and negative-duration tokens
      (where <tt>exp &lt;= iat</tt>) MUST be rejected.
    </t>
    <t>
      REMINDER: A token's Tier is determined by its highest-risk scope
      (Section 3.1). A token containing one Tier 2 scope and any number of
      Tier 1 scopes is a Tier 2 token in its entirety. Implementations
      MUST NOT derive Tier from the majority of scopes or from the first
      scope in the array.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="token-refresh" numbered="true">
    <name>Token Refresh and Long-Running Tasks</name>

    <section anchor="agent-self-refresh" numbered="true">
      <name>Agent Self-Refresh</name>
      <t>
        An AIP agent holds its own Ed25519 private key and MAY issue new
        Credential Tokens at any time, provided the Principal Token(s) in its
        delegation chain (<tt>aip_chain</tt>) remain valid. There is no refresh token
        in AIP - the agent's signing key IS the refresh credential.
      </t>
      <t>
        An agent self-refresh involves: issuing a new Credential Token with a
        new <tt>jti</tt>, a fresh <tt>iat</tt>, and a new <tt>exp</tt> within TTL limits.
        The <tt>aip_chain</tt> content remains unchanged until the Principal Tokens
        within it expire.
      </t>
      <t>
        Agents MUST NOT re-use the same <tt>jti</tt> when issuing a fresh token.
        Each issued Credential Token MUST have a unique <tt>jti</tt>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="preemptive-refresh" numbered="true">
      <name>Pre-emptive Refresh Requirements</name>
      <t>
        Agents MUST implement pre-emptive refresh to avoid mid-task token
        expiry. An agent MUST begin issuing a replacement Credential Token
        before the current token expires:
      </t>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr><th>Token TTL Category</th><th>Begin refresh when remaining TTL &lt;=</th></tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr><td>Standard (3600s)</td><td>300 seconds (5 minutes)</td></tr>
          <tr><td>Sensitive (300s)</td><td>30 seconds</td></tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>
        Implementations MUST NOT wait for a token rejection
        (<tt>token_expired</tt>) before refreshing. Waiting for rejection
        creates a gap in execution continuity and may leave in-progress Tier 2
        operations without valid authority.
      </t>
      <t>
        Relying Parties MUST NOT reject a token solely because a newer token
        exists for the same agent. Each token is independently valid for its
        own <tt>iat</tt> to <tt>exp</tt> window.
      </t>
      <t>
        For real-time streaming interactions (e.g., a long-running web
        socket), the agent SHOULD renegotiate the session with a fresh
        Credential Token before the current token's expiry rather than
        waiting for mid-stream rejection.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="delegation-chain-expiry" numbered="true">
      <name>Delegation Chain Expiry</name>
      <t>
        When a Principal Token in the <tt>aip_chain</tt> expires, the Credential
        Token becomes structurally invalid at validation Step 8h regardless
        of the Credential Token's own <tt>exp</tt>. This is because the delegation
        authority itself has lapsed.
      </t>
      <t>
        When a delegation chain expires:
      </t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li>The agent MUST NOT issue new Credential Tokens referencing the expired <tt>aip_chain</tt> (even if the agent's own <tt>exp</tt> is still in the future).</li>
        <li>The agent MUST obtain a fresh delegation from its parent (or from the root principal for depth-0 agents) via the AIP-GRANT flow or sub-agent delegation flow.</li>
        <li>Once a fresh delegation is established and registered, the agent may resume issuing Credential Tokens.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>
        Relying Parties that receive a token where Step 8h fails MUST return
        <tt>chain_token_expired</tt>. Agents receiving this error MUST treat it as
        <tt>delegation_chain_refresh_required</tt> - they must re-establish their
        delegation rather than merely refreshing their Credential Token.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>Anticipatory chain refresh:</strong> Agents SHOULD monitor the
        <tt>expires_at</tt> timestamps of all Principal Tokens in their
        <tt>aip_chain</tt>. When the nearest expiry is within 10% of the total
        delegation validity period (or 24 hours, whichever is smaller), the
        agent SHOULD proactively initiate a delegation renewal.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="approval-envelope-interaction" numbered="true">
      <name>Interaction with Approval Envelopes</name>
      <t>
        Approval Envelopes are specifically designed to decouple
        human approval timing from token TTL constraints. The following rules
        govern their interaction:
      </t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li>An Approval Envelope's <tt>approval_window_expires_at</tt> is independent of any Credential Token TTL. Envelopes may remain in <tt>pending_approval</tt> status for hours while normal TTLs of 300s or 3600s apply only at execution time.</li>
        <li>When an agent claims an Approval Step, it MUST present a Credential Token that is valid at the time of the claim. The token TTL for a step-claim follows the same rules as for any other interaction involving those scopes (300s for Tier 2 scopes, 3600s for Tier 1).</li>
        <li>Long-running workflows where steps are separated by hours or days require the agent to issue a fresh Credential Token for each step claim. This is intentional - the agent's authority must be re-verified at each step, not just at envelope creation time.</li>
        <li>If an agent's delegation chain expires between envelope approval and step execution, the agent MUST renew its delegation before claiming any remaining steps. The Approval Envelope itself remains valid - only the execution credential needs renewal.</li>
        <li>An agent MUST NOT pre-issue step-claim Credential Tokens for all steps at envelope approval time. Tokens MUST be issued at execution time so that revocation checks (Section 7.2 Step 7) are performed against the current Registry state.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="token-exchange-mcp" numbered="true">
    <name>Token Exchange for MCP</name>

    <section anchor="token-exchange-overview" numbered="true">
      <name>Overview</name>
      <t>
        An AIP agent MAY exchange its Credential Token for a scoped access
        token targeting a specific MCP server or OAuth-protected resource.
        The exchange is performed at the Registry's token endpoint
       .
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="token-exchange-request" numbered="true">
      <name>Exchange Request</name>
      <t>
        The agent sends an RFC 8693 token exchange request:
      </t>
      <sourcecode><![CDATA[
 POST /v1/oauth/token HTTP/1.1
 Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
 DPoP: <DPoP proof JWT>

 grant_type=urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:token-exchange
 &subject_token=<AIP Credential Token>
 &subject_token_type=urn:ietf:params:oauth:token-type:jwt
 &resource=https://mcp-server.example.com/
 &scope=urn:aip:scope:email.read urn:aip:scope:calendar.read
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>Normative requirements:</t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li><tt>grant_type</tt> MUST be <tt>urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:token-exchange</tt>.</li>
        <li><tt>subject_token</tt> MUST be a valid AIP Credential Token.</li>
        <li><tt>subject_token_type</tt> MUST be <tt>urn:ietf:params:oauth:token-type:jwt</tt>.</li>
        <li><tt>resource</tt> MUST be present per RFC 8707 <xref target="RFC8707"/>, identifying the target resource server.</li>
        <li><tt>scope</tt> MUST use AIP scope URIs from the <tt>urn:aip:scope:</tt> namespace. The requested scopes MUST be a subset of the Credential Token's <tt>aip_scope</tt>.</li>
        <li>DPoP proof <xref target="RFC9449"/> MUST be included, binding the exchange to the agent's key material.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section anchor="token-exchange-validation" numbered="true">
      <name>Exchange Validation</name>
      <t>
        The Registry (as OAuth AS) MUST:
      </t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li>Validate the <tt>subject_token</tt> using the full validation algorithm.</li>
        <li>Verify the DPoP proof binds to the agent's public key.</li>
        <li>Verify the requested <tt>scope</tt> is a subset of the <tt>subject_token</tt>'s <tt>aip_scope</tt> (attenuation only, never expansion).</li>
        <li>Verify the <tt>resource</tt> is a registered MCP server or resource. Fail: <tt>invalid_target</tt>.</li>
        <li>
          <t>Issue an access token with:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><t><tt>aud</tt> set to the <tt>resource</tt> URI</t></li>
            <li><t><tt>scope</tt> set to the granted scopes</t></li>
            <li><t><tt>sub</tt> set to the agent's AID</t></li>
            <li><t><tt>act.sub</tt> set to the root principal's DID (actor chain per <xref target="RFC8693"/> §4.1)</t></li>
            <li><t>TTL &lt;= the remaining TTL of the <tt>subject_token</tt></t></li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>The access token MUST be a JWT per RFC 9068 <xref target="RFC9068"/>.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section anchor="token-exchange-response" numbered="true">
      <name>Exchange Response</name>
      <t>EXAMPLE (informative):</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
 {
   "access_token": "<JWT>",
   "token_type": "DPoP",
   "expires_in": 300,
   "scope": "urn:aip:scope:email.read urn:aip:scope:calendar.read",
"issued_token_type": "urn:ietf:params:oauth:token-type:access_token"
 }
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
