<section anchor="credential-tokens" numbered="true">
  <name>Credential Tokens</name>

  <section anchor="token-structure" numbered="true">
    <name>Credential Token Transport and Version Header</name>
    <t>
      The Credential Token JWT header and payload fields are defined in
      Section 5.4. This section defines only the HTTP transport profile,
      version-header requirements, issuance lifetime rules, and refresh
      behavior for those tokens.
    </t>
    <t>
      An AIP Credential Token for a request that does not require
      proof-of-possession is transmitted as an HTTP Authorization header using
      the registered Bearer authentication scheme <xref target="RFC6750"/>:
    </t>
    <t>EXAMPLE (informative):</t>
    <sourcecode><![CDATA[
 Authorization: Bearer <token>
 X-AIP-Version: 0.3
]]></sourcecode>
    <t>
      For interactions requiring Proof-of-Possession, the Credential Token is
      transmitted using the registered DPoP authentication scheme
      <xref target="RFC9449"/> and the request also carries a DPoP proof JWT:
    </t>
    <t>EXAMPLE (informative):</t>
    <sourcecode><![CDATA[
 Authorization: DPoP <token>
 DPoP: <dpop-proof>
 X-AIP-Version: 0.3
]]></sourcecode>
    <t>
      The <tt>X-AIP-Version</tt> HTTP header MUST carry the full protocol
      version string, identical to the <tt>aip_version</tt> JWT claim. For
      this specification, the value MUST be
      <tt>"0.3"</tt>. This value is the AIP protocol compatibility version
      defined in Section 20, not the Internet-Draft revision suffix.
      Implementations MUST reject requests with <tt>unsupported_version</tt>
      when the <tt>X-AIP-Version</tt> header is absent, carries an unsupported
      value, or does not match the token <tt>aip_version</tt> claim.
    </t>
    <t>
      Every AIP-aware HTTP response to an AIP protocol request MUST include
      an <tt>X-AIP-Version</tt> response header containing the AIP protocol
      compatibility version used to interpret the request and generate the
      response. For responses conforming to this specification, the value
      MUST be <tt>"0.3"</tt>. This requirement applies to successful
      responses and error responses, including responses that reject a
      request with <tt>unsupported_version</tt>. When a request is rejected
      because the requested version is unsupported, the responder MUST set
      <tt>X-AIP-Version</tt> to a protocol version it supports for that
      endpoint and SHOULD include <tt>X-AIP-Supported-Versions</tt> with a
      comma-separated list of supported AIP protocol versions.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="token-issuance" numbered="true">
    <name>Token Issuance</name>
    <t>
      Implementations MUST enforce the following maximum Credential Token
      lifetimes. The effective TTL limit for a token is the lowest applicable
      limit from this table across all requested scopes.
    </t>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr><th>Scope Category</th><th>Maximum TTL</th></tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr><td>Tier 1 scope</td><td>3600 seconds, unless the synced AIP Scope Catalog entry sets a lower <tt>ttl_max_seconds</tt></td></tr>
        <tr><td>Tier 2 scope</td><td>300 seconds, unless the synced AIP Scope Catalog entry sets a lower <tt>ttl_max_seconds</tt></td></tr>
        <tr><td>Tier 3 scope</td><td>300 seconds, unless the synced AIP Scope Catalog entry sets a lower <tt>ttl_max_seconds</tt></td></tr>
        <tr><td>Any requested scope</td><td>The <tt>ttl_max_seconds</tt> value in the synced AIP Scope Catalog entry for that scope, capped by the Tier ceiling above</td></tr>
        <tr><td>Multiple scopes in one token</td><td>The lowest <tt>ttl_max_seconds</tt> value across all requested scopes</td></tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <t>
      When a token contains multiple scopes, the most restrictive TTL applies.
      Zero-duration and negative-duration tokens
      (where <tt>exp &lt;= iat</tt>) MUST be rejected.
      A synced AIP Scope Catalog entry for a standard or extension scope MUST
      NOT advertise a <tt>ttl_max_seconds</tt> value greater than the ceiling
      for that scope's Tier. A token containing a scope whose active catalog
      entry is missing, inactive, or exceeds its Tier ceiling MUST be rejected
      with <tt>invalid_scope</tt> or <tt>invalid_token</tt> as applicable to the
      validation step.
    </t>
    <t>
      A token's security Tier is determined by its highest-risk scope
      (<xref target="architecture-tiers"/>). A token containing one Tier 2 scope and any number of
      Tier 1 scopes is a Tier 2 token in its entirety. Implementations
      MUST NOT derive Tier from the majority of scopes or from the first
      scope in the array.
    </t>

    <section anchor="token-cache-requirements-stateless" numbered="true">
      <name>Token Cache Requirements for Stateless Deployments</name>
      <t>
        AIP Registries and Relying Parties operating in stateless transport
        environments, including MCP stateless transport
        <xref target="MCP-STATELESS"/>, or horizontally-scaled deployments
        MUST store validated Credential Token cache entries in a shared,
        externally-accessible store, such as Redis or a distributed key-value
        store, that is accessible to all instances that may validate tokens for
        the same AID. Local in-process or filesystem-backed caches are
        PERMITTED only in single-instance development deployments and MUST NOT
        be used in a Production Deployment as defined in
        <xref target="terminology"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        A validation cache entry MUST be keyed by
        <tt>SHA-256(exact-compact-token)</tt>, not by <tt>jti</tt> alone.
        The cache entry MUST include:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>the token <tt>iss</tt> and <tt>jti</tt> for replay-cache
        correlation;</li>
        <li>the token <tt>exp</tt> as the maximum cache TTL;</li>
        <li>the cached Registry-dependent validation subresults and their
        freshness sources;</li>
        <li>the set of validation step identifiers whose results were cached;
        and</li>
        <li>the validated AIP Tier.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        A cache entry is an optimization for previously completed validation,
        not a replacement for the validation algorithm. Implementations MAY
        reuse cached Registry-dependent validation results only when the
        token's Tier and the relevant validation step permit bounded
        staleness. For Tier 2 and Tier 3 tokens, a cached accepted result MUST
        NOT bypass the live revocation lookup required by
        <xref target="revocation-checking"/> and <xref target="validation-step-7"/>.
        Per-request checks that are not cacheable, including
        proof-of-possession, mTLS, audience matching, expiration, and replay
        policy, remain in force for every interaction. A cached accepted
        result MUST NOT cause a token whose <tt>(iss, jti)</tt> pair has
        already been consumed to be accepted again. This cache prevents
        redundant Registry round-trips only for validation results whose
        freshness rules allow reuse.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="token-refresh" numbered="true">
    <name>Token Refresh and Long-Running Tasks</name>

    <section anchor="agent-self-refresh" numbered="true">
      <name>Agent Self-Refresh</name>
      <t>
        An AIP agent holds its own Ed25519 private key and MAY issue new
        Credential Tokens at any time, provided the Principal Token(s) in its
        delegation chain (<tt>aip_chain</tt>) remain valid. There is no refresh token
        in AIP - the agent's signing key IS the refresh credential.
      </t>
      <t>
        An agent self-refresh involves: issuing a new Credential Token with a
        new <tt>jti</tt>, a fresh <tt>iat</tt>, and a new <tt>exp</tt> within TTL limits.
        The <tt>aip_chain</tt> content remains unchanged until the Principal Tokens
        within it expire.
      </t>
      <t>
        Agents MUST NOT re-use the same <tt>jti</tt> when issuing a fresh token.
        Each issued Credential Token MUST have a unique <tt>jti</tt> across
        all tokens issued by that agent AID. This uniqueness requirement is
        independent of <tt>aip_chain</tt>, principal DID, registration grant,
        scope set, or audience. An agent delegated by multiple principals
        MUST still maintain a single <tt>jti</tt> uniqueness domain for its
        issuer AID.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="preemptive-refresh" numbered="true">
      <name>Pre-emptive Refresh Requirements</name>
      <t>
        Agents MUST implement pre-emptive refresh to avoid mid-task token
        expiry. An agent MUST begin issuing a replacement Credential Token
        before the current token expires. The refresh threshold is derived
        from the token's effective TTL, not from a fixed Tier label:
      </t>
      <sourcecode><![CDATA[
effective_ttl_seconds = exp - iat

refresh_lead_seconds =
  max(1, min(
    300,
    max(30, ceiling(effective_ttl_seconds * 0.10)),
    floor(effective_ttl_seconds / 2)
  ))

begin refresh when (exp - now) <= refresh_lead_seconds
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>
        This formula preserves the former 300-second refresh lead for a
        3600-second catalog TTL and the former 30-second refresh lead for a
        300-second catalog TTL, while remaining valid for future catalog TTL
        values.
      </t>
      <t>
        Implementations MUST NOT wait for a token rejection
        (<tt>token_expired</tt>) before refreshing. Waiting for rejection
        creates a gap in execution continuity and may leave in-progress Tier 2
        operations without valid authority.
      </t>
      <t>
        Relying Parties MUST NOT reject a token solely because a newer token
        exists for the same agent. Each token is independently valid for its
        own <tt>iat</tt> to <tt>exp</tt> window.
      </t>
      <t>
        For real-time streaming interactions (e.g., a long-running web
        socket), the agent SHOULD renegotiate the session with a fresh
        Credential Token before the current token's expiry rather than
        waiting for mid-stream rejection.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="delegation-chain-expiry" numbered="true">
      <name>Delegation Chain Expiry</name>
      <t>
        When a Principal Token in the <tt>aip_chain</tt> expires, the Credential
        Token becomes structurally invalid at validation Step 8h regardless
        of the Credential Token's own <tt>exp</tt>. This is because the delegation
        authority itself has lapsed.
      </t>
      <t>
        When a delegation chain expires:
      </t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li>The agent MUST NOT issue new Credential Tokens referencing the expired <tt>aip_chain</tt> (even if the agent's own <tt>exp</tt> is still in the future).</li>
        <li>The agent MUST obtain a fresh delegation from its parent (or from the root principal for depth-0 agents) via the AIP-GRANT flow or sub-agent delegation flow.</li>
        <li>Once a fresh delegation is established and registered, the agent may resume issuing Credential Tokens.</li>
      </ol>
      <t>
        Relying Parties that receive a token where Step 8h fails MUST return
        <tt>chain_token_expired</tt>. Agents receiving this error MUST
        re-establish their delegation rather than merely refreshing their
        Credential Token. AIP does not define a separate on-wire error code
        for "delegation refresh required"; chain renewal is the required
        agent-side handling of <tt>chain_token_expired</tt>.
      </t>
      <t>
        <strong>Anticipatory chain refresh:</strong> Agents SHOULD monitor the
        <tt>expires_at</tt> timestamps of all Principal Tokens in their
        <tt>aip_chain</tt>. When the nearest expiry is within 10% of the total
        delegation validity period (or 24 hours, whichever is smaller), the
        agent SHOULD proactively initiate a delegation renewal.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="approval-envelope-interaction" numbered="true">
      <name>Interaction with Approval Envelopes</name>
      <t>
        Approval Envelopes are specifically designed to decouple
        human approval timing from token TTL constraints. The following rules
        govern their interaction:
      </t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li>An Approval Envelope's <tt>approval_window_expires_at</tt> is independent of any Credential Token TTL. Envelopes may remain in <tt>pending_approval</tt> status for hours while catalog-derived Credential Token TTLs apply only at execution time.</li>
        <li>When an agent claims an Approval Step, it MUST present a Credential Token that is valid at the time of the claim. The token TTL for a step-claim follows the same <xref target="token-issuance"/> catalog-derived rules as for any other interaction involving those scopes.</li>
        <li>Long-running workflows where steps are separated by hours or days require the agent to issue a fresh Credential Token for each step claim. This is intentional - the agent's authority must be re-verified at each step, not just at envelope creation time.</li>
        <li>If an agent's delegation chain expires between envelope approval and step execution, the agent MUST renew its delegation before claiming any remaining steps. The Approval Envelope itself remains valid - only the execution credential needs renewal.</li>
        <li>An agent MUST NOT pre-issue step-claim Credential Tokens for all steps at envelope approval time. Tokens MUST be issued at execution time so that revocation checks (Section 9 Step 7) are performed against the current Registry state.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="token-exchange-mcp" numbered="true">
    <name>Token Exchange for MCP</name>

    <section anchor="token-exchange-overview" numbered="true">
      <name>Overview</name>
      <t>
        An AIP agent MAY exchange its Credential Token for a scoped access
        token targeting a specific MCP server or OAuth-protected resource.
        The exchange is performed at the Registry's token endpoint
       .
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="token-exchange-request" numbered="true">
      <name>Exchange Request</name>
      <t>
        The agent sends an RFC 8693 token exchange request:
      </t>
      <sourcecode><![CDATA[
 POST /v1/oauth/token HTTP/1.1
 Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
 DPoP: <DPoP proof JWT>

 grant_type=urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:token-exchange
 &subject_token=<AIP Credential Token>
 &subject_token_type=urn:ietf:params:oauth:token-type:jwt
 &resource=https://mcp-server.example.com/
 &scope=email.read calendar.read
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>Normative requirements:</t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li><tt>grant_type</tt> MUST be <tt>urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:token-exchange</tt>.</li>
        <li><tt>subject_token</tt> MUST be a valid AIP Credential Token.</li>
        <li><tt>subject_token_type</tt> MUST be <tt>urn:ietf:params:oauth:token-type:jwt</tt>.</li>
        <li><tt>resource</tt> MUST be present per RFC 8707 <xref target="RFC8707"/>, identifying the target resource server. For OAuth-protected resources, the value MUST be an RFC 9728 <xref target="RFC9728"/> resource identifier.</li>
        <li><tt>scope</tt> MUST use AIP scope strings from the synced AIP Scope Catalog or accepted local extension policy. The requested scopes MUST be a subset of the Credential Token's <tt>aip_scope</tt>.</li>
        <li>DPoP proof <xref target="RFC9449"/> MUST be included, binding the exchange to the agent's key material.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section anchor="token-exchange-validation" numbered="true">
      <name>Exchange Validation</name>
      <t>
        The Registry (as OAuth AS) MUST:
      </t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li>Validate the <tt>subject_token</tt> using the full validation algorithm.</li>
        <li>Verify the DPoP proof binds to the agent's public key.</li>
        <li>Verify the requested <tt>scope</tt> is a subset of the <tt>subject_token</tt>'s <tt>aip_scope</tt> (attenuation only, never expansion).</li>
        <li>
          <t>Verify the <tt>resource</tt> identifies a registered MCP server
          or OAuth-protected resource. The Registry MUST perform this check
          using at least one of the following mechanisms:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><t>match the <tt>resource</tt> URI against a Registry-local
            registration record for an MCP server or protected resource; or</t></li>
            <li><t>obtain the resource's Protected Resource Metadata using
            RFC 9728 <xref target="RFC9728"/> and verify that the returned
            <tt>resource</tt> metadata value is the same resource identifier
            as the requested <tt>resource</tt>.</t></li>
          </ul>
          <t>
            When RFC 9728 metadata is used, the metadata MUST identify an
            authorization server acceptable to the Registry, either by listing
            the Registry's OAuth authorization-server issuer identifier in
            <tt>authorization_servers</tt> or by satisfying an equivalent
            local trust policy. The Registry MUST reject with
            <tt>invalid_target</tt> if metadata retrieval fails, the returned
            <tt>resource</tt> value does not match the requested
            <tt>resource</tt>, the resource is not locally registered, or no
            acceptable authorization server relationship is established.
          </t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>Issue an access token with:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><t><tt>aud</tt> set to the <tt>resource</tt> URI</t></li>
            <li><t><tt>scope</tt> set to the granted scopes</t></li>
            <li><t><tt>sub</tt> set to the agent's AID</t></li>
            <li><t><tt>act.sub</tt> set to the root principal's DID (actor chain per <xref target="RFC8693"/> §4.1)</t></li>
            <li><t>TTL &lt;= the remaining TTL of the <tt>subject_token</tt></t></li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>The access token MUST be a JWT per RFC 9068 <xref target="RFC9068"/>.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section anchor="token-exchange-response" numbered="true">
      <name>Exchange Response</name>
      <t>EXAMPLE (informative):</t>
      <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
 {
   "access_token": "<JWT>",
   "token_type": "DPoP",
   "expires_in": 300,
   "scope": "email.read calendar.read",
"issued_token_type": "urn:ietf:params:oauth:token-type:access_token"
 }
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>

    <section anchor="enterprise-idp-federation-profile" numbered="true">
      <name>Enterprise IdP Federation Profile</name>
      <t>
        When the target resource in a token exchange request is registered in
        the Registry with <tt>enterprise_idp_required: true</tt> (see
        <xref target="resource-registration-registry"/>), the AIP
        Registry acting as intermediary MUST perform a secondary token
        exchange with the configured Enterprise IdP. The Registry MUST NOT
        perform the enterprise IdP leg for resources registered with
        <tt>enterprise_idp_required: false</tt> or with
        <tt>enterprise_idp_required</tt> absent. Enterprise integrations such
        as Microsoft Entra Agent ID <xref target="MS-ENTRAAGENTID"/> can use
        this profile when the resource registration record requires it.
      </t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li>The AIP Registry validates the inbound AIP Credential Token per
        <xref target="credential-token-validation"/>.</li>
        <li>
          <t>The Registry constructs a signed JWT assertion using its
          registered client identity with the enterprise IdP. The assertion
          MUST include:</t>
          <ul>
            <li><tt>iss</tt>: the AIP Registry's <tt>client_id</tt>
            registered with the enterprise IdP;</li>
            <li><tt>sub</tt>: the agent's AID;</li>
            <li><tt>aud</tt>: the enterprise IdP token endpoint URI;</li>
            <li><tt>aip_sub_principal</tt>: the root Principal Token
            <tt>principal.id</tt> value from the validated
            <tt>aip_chain</tt>;</li>
            <li><tt>aip_scopes</tt>: the validated <tt>aip_scope</tt> values
            from the Credential Token.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>The Registry submits this assertion to the enterprise IdP token
        endpoint using
        <tt>grant_type=urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:jwt-bearer</tt> per
        RFC 7523 <xref target="RFC7523"/> or
        <tt>grant_type=urn:ietf:params:oauth:grant-type:token-exchange</tt>
        per RFC 8693 <xref target="RFC8693"/>.</li>
        <li>The enterprise IdP evaluates the request against its Conditional
        Access, ABAC, and equivalent enterprise access policies using
        <tt>aip_sub_principal</tt> as the human or organizational principal
        context and the agent AID as the client identity.</li>
        <li>On success, the enterprise IdP issues an access token scoped to
        the target resource.</li>
        <li>The AIP Registry returns the enterprise-issued token in the token
        exchange response.</li>
      </ol>

      <section anchor="enterprise-assertion-jwt-schema" numbered="true">
        <name>Enterprise Assertion JWT Schema</name>
        <t>
          The JWT assertion constructed by the Registry for the enterprise IdP
          token endpoint MUST contain the following payload fields:
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Field</th><th>Type</th><th>Required</th><th>Constraints</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td><tt>iss</tt></td><td>string</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>MUST be the AIP Registry's <tt>client_id</tt> as registered with the enterprise IdP. MUST NOT be the Registry's <tt>registry_id</tt>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>sub</tt></td><td>string</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>MUST be the acting agent's AID.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>aud</tt></td><td>string or array</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>MUST be the enterprise IdP's token endpoint URI.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>aip_sub_principal</tt></td><td>string</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>MUST be the root Principal Token <tt>principal.id</tt> value from <tt>aip_chain[0]</tt> of the validated Credential Token. MUST be a valid W3C DID.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>aip_scopes</tt></td><td>array of strings</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>MUST be the validated <tt>aip_scope</tt> values from the Credential Token. MUST NOT include scopes not present in the validated Credential Token.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>iat</tt></td><td>integer</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Unix timestamp representing the current time at assertion construction.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>exp</tt></td><td>integer</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Unix timestamp. MUST be <tt>iat + 60</tt> or earlier. Registries MUST NOT issue assertions with <tt>exp - iat &gt; 60</tt>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>jti</tt></td><td>string</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>UUID v4. MUST be unique per assertion to prevent replay.</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="enterprise-idp-error-handling" numbered="true">
        <name>Enterprise IdP Error Handling</name>
        <t>
          When the enterprise IdP token endpoint returns an error or cannot be
          reached, the AIP Registry MUST map the result to the agent-facing
          AIP response as follows:
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Enterprise IdP Response</th><th>AIP Registry Response to Agent</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td>HTTP 400 (<tt>invalid_request</tt>)</td><td>HTTP 400, error: <tt>invalid_request</tt></td></tr>
            <tr><td>HTTP 400 (<tt>invalid_client</tt>)</td><td>HTTP 500, error: <tt>idp_client_misconfigured</tt></td></tr>
            <tr><td>HTTP 400 (<tt>invalid_grant</tt>)</td><td>HTTP 400, error: <tt>invalid_grant</tt></td></tr>
            <tr><td>HTTP 400 (<tt>unauthorized_client</tt>)</td><td>HTTP 403, error: <tt>insufficient_scope</tt></td></tr>
            <tr><td>HTTP 403 (<tt>access_denied</tt> or Conditional Access denial)</td><td>HTTP 403, error: <tt>enterprise_policy_denied</tt></td></tr>
            <tr><td>HTTP 4xx (other)</td><td>HTTP 400, error: <tt>invalid_request</tt></td></tr>
            <tr><td>HTTP 5xx</td><td>HTTP 503, error: <tt>registry_unavailable</tt></td></tr>
            <tr><td>Timeout greater than 5 seconds</td><td>HTTP 503, error: <tt>registry_unavailable</tt></td></tr>
            <tr><td>TLS or network error</td><td>HTTP 503, error: <tt>registry_unavailable</tt></td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>
          The Registry MUST NOT expose raw enterprise IdP error messages to
          the calling agent. When <tt>enterprise_policy_denied</tt> is
          returned, the <tt>error_description</tt> SHOULD indicate that the
          request was denied by enterprise policy without revealing specific
          policy rules. The Registry MUST log the full enterprise IdP response
          for audit purposes per <xref target="key-management"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="enterprise-idp-federation-metadata" numbered="true">
        <name>Federation Metadata and Grant Tier Guidance</name>
        <t>
          AIP Registries that support this profile MUST advertise
          <tt>enterprise_idp_federation_supported: true</tt> in their
          <tt>/v1/registry-metadata</tt> metadata as described by
          <xref target="registry-genesis-well-known-publication"/> and
          <xref target="well-known-metadata-registry"/>. Relying Parties and
          agents MUST NOT infer federation support from absence of this field.
        </t>
        <t>
          Enterprise deployments using this profile SHOULD require G3 grants
          from <xref target="principal-grant"/> for the root Principal Token so
          that human authentication context and IdP policy context are
          available during token exchange and Tier 3 validation.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
