<section anchor="delegation-rules" numbered="true">
  <name>Delegation</name>
  <t>     AIP enables hierarchical delegation where a principal authorizes a     primary agent, which may in turn authorize sub-agents under narrowing    scope constraints. Delegation is encoded in the <tt>aip_chain</tt> array
    of the Credential Token, with each Principal Token in the chain
    representing one delegation hop from principal to agent.
  </t>

  <section anchor="delegation-chain" numbered="true">
  <name>Delegation Chain</name>
    <t>
      Every Credential Token MUST include a verifiable principal chain
      linking the acting agent to its root principal via the
      <tt>aip_chain</tt> array. The root principal MUST be a human or
      organizational entity identified by a W3C Decentralized Identifier
      (DID) that does NOT use the <tt>did:aip</tt> method. For example:
      <tt>did:web</tt>, <tt>did:key</tt>, or proprietary DID methods are
      acceptable.
    </t>
    <t>
      The maximum delegation depth is a hard constraint of 10 levels. This
      means an agent may not delegate to a sub-agent if doing so would
      create a chain longer than 10 Principal Tokens (0-indexed from 0 to
      9, or 1-indexed as depths 1 to 10).
    </t>
    <t>
      The default value of <tt>max_delegation_depth</tt> MUST NOT exceed 3.
      When a Principal Token does not explicitly set
      <tt>max_delegation_depth</tt>, implementations MUST treat the default
      as 3. This conservative default prevents accidental authorization
      chains from becoming unmanageably deep; parties requiring deeper
      chains MUST explicitly opt in by setting
      <tt>max_delegation_depth</tt> to a value between 3 and 10.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="scope-inheritance-rules" numbered="true">
  <name>Capability Scope Rules</name>
    <t>
      Scope inheritance is the mechanism by which child agents are
      constrained to operate within the bounds of their parent's
      authorization. Five core rules (D-1 through D-5) govern this
      relationship; they are defined in Section 4.2.10 of the AIP
      specification.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>Scope Inheritance Rule:</strong> For each scope <tt>s</tt>
      granted to a child agent, <tt>s</tt> MUST be present in the parent's
      Capability Manifest AND all constraint values for <tt>s</tt> in the
      child's manifest MUST be no more permissive (&lt;=) than the corresponding
      values in the parent's manifest.
    </t>
    <t>
      For numeric limits (e.g., <tt>max_single_transaction</tt>,
      <tt>max_daily_value</tt>), the child value MUST be &lt;= the parent value.
      For boolean enables or enum values, the child constraint MUST NOT be
      more permissive than the parent (e.g., child cannot set a flag
      <tt>true</tt> if parent sets it <tt>false</tt>).
    </t>
    <t>
      Implementations MUST enforce this rule at delegation time -- when a
      child agent is registered, the Registry MUST validate that all scopes
      in its Capability Manifest satisfy the inheritance rule relative to
      its immediate parent's manifest. Implementations MAY reject delegation
      requests that violate this rule before they are registered.
    </t>
    <t>
      Relying Parties MUST independently verify this rule during validation
      at Step 9c of the Credential Token validation algorithm (see
      <xref target="validation-step-9"/>). This ensures that even if a
      Registry incorrectly permits a violating delegation, Relying Parties
      will catch it and reject the token.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="delegation-validation" numbered="true">
  <name>Delegation Validation</name>
    <t>
      When validating a delegated Credential Token, Relying Parties must
      fetch and verify the Capability Manifests of all agents in the
      delegation chain. This section specifies the performance and caching
      constraints for these operations.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>Ancestor Manifest Fetch Limits:</strong> Implementations MUST
      NOT fetch more ancestor manifests than the <tt>max_delegation_depth</tt>
      value of the chain's root token (which defaults to 3 when absent).
      This limit prevents accidental O(n^2) fetch patterns in deep delegation
      chains and bounds the performance cost of validation.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>Ancestor Manifest Caching for Tier 1:</strong> For Tier 1
      operations (low-risk scopes with bounded-staleness threat model),
      ancestor manifests MAY be cached for a maximum of 60 seconds. This
      cache is per-agent and per-manifest, and MUST respect the 60-second
      TTL. After 60 seconds, a fresh fetch is required.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>No-Cache Requirement for Tier 2:</strong> For Tier 2 operations
      (high-risk scopes with real-time threat model), the no-cache
      requirement in the Credential Token validation algorithm (see
      <xref target="validation-step-9"/>) applies to ALL manifests in the
      delegation chain -- including ancestor manifests -- not only the leaf
      agent's manifest. The 60-second ancestor cache MUST NOT be used for
      any manifest appearing in a Tier 2 validation. Every manifest must be
      fetched fresh from the Registry.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>Unavailable Manifests:</strong> If an ancestor manifest is
      unavailable or cannot be fetched (due to network failure, Registry
      downtime, or the manifest having been deleted), the Relying Party MUST
      reject the token by returning the error code <tt>manifest_invalid</tt>.
      Partial delegation chains are not acceptable; either all manifests in
      the chain are available and valid, or the token is rejected.
    </t>
  </section>

</section>
