<section anchor="revocation" numbered="true">
  <name>Revocation Management</name>
  <t>
    Revocation provides the kill switch for agent identity. When
    an agent is revoked, its Credential Tokens and Step Execution Tokens MUST
    be rejected as soon as the applicable revocation check observes the active
    revocation. Tier 2 and Tier 3 checks are live and fail closed on Registry
    unavailability. Tier 1 uses bounded-staleness CRLs, so enforcement can
    lag until the next fresh CRL within the SLA defined in this section.
  </t>

  <section anchor="revocation-object" numbered="true">
  <name>Revocation Object</name>
    <t>
      Revocation is performed by submitting a signed Revocation Object to
      <tt>POST /v1/revocations</tt>. The Revocation Object fields, required
      members, type enum, and signing input are defined only in Section 5.7.
      This section defines processing effects for accepted Revocation Objects;
      it does not define a second Revocation Object schema.
    </t>
    <t>
      A <tt>principal_revoke</tt> with a Principal DID target invalidates
      every Credential Token and Step Execution Token whose
      <tt>aip_chain[0].principal.id</tt> equals that Principal DID. A
      <tt>principal_revoke</tt> with an AID target invalidates every token
      whose <tt>aip_chain</tt> depends on that AID's principal authorisation.
      This effect is independent of <tt>propagate_to_children</tt>.
      The <tt>propagate_to_children</tt> flag controls whether the Registry
      also materialises descendant Revocation Objects; it does not limit the
      validity effect of <tt>principal_revoke</tt>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="revocation-submission-validation" numbered="true">
  <name>Revocation Submission Validation</name>
    <t>
      A conformant Registry MUST implement <tt>POST /v1/revocations</tt> for
      externally submitted Revocation Objects. The request body MUST be a JSON
      object conforming to <tt>revocation-object.schema.json</tt>. Unless a
      check below specifies a more precise error code, failed validation MUST
      be rejected with <tt>revocation_invalid</tt>.
    </t>

    <t>
      The Registry MUST perform the following checks in order:
    </t>
    <ol>
      <li>The request MUST use <tt>Content-Type: application/json</tt>. The
      object MUST contain all required Revocation Object members, including
      <tt>kid</tt>. If <tt>propagate_to_children</tt> is absent, the Registry
      MUST process it as <tt>false</tt>.</li>
      <li>If <tt>revocation_id</tt> was already accepted, the Registry MUST
      compare the Section 2.1 canonical JSON serialization of the submitted
      object to the stored object. If they are identical, the Registry MUST
      return HTTP 200 with the stored Revocation Object and MUST NOT apply side
      effects again. If they differ, the Registry MUST reject with
      <tt>revocation_conflict</tt>.</li>
      <li>The <tt>timestamp</tt> value MUST be a valid UTC date-time and MUST
      NOT be more than 300 seconds in the future relative to the Registry's
      current clock. Registries MAY accept older timestamps, but the
      <tt>revocation_id</tt> uniqueness check remains mandatory.</li>
      <li>The <tt>reason</tt> value MUST be one of the reason codes in the
      Revocation Object schema. Externally submitted Revocation Objects MUST
      NOT use <tt>parent_revoked</tt>, <tt>heartbeat_timeout</tt>, or
      <tt>lifecycle_expired</tt>; those reason codes are reserved for
      Registry-generated Revocation Objects.</li>
      <li>For <tt>full_revoke</tt>, <tt>scope_revoke</tt>, and
      <tt>delegation_revoke</tt>, <tt>target_id</tt> MUST be a registered
      <tt>did:aip</tt> AID in the authoritative Registry. Unknown targets
      MUST be rejected with <tt>unknown_aid</tt>. For
      <tt>principal_revoke</tt>, <tt>target_id</tt> MUST be either a
      registered AID or a Principal DID associated with at least one stored
      registration in that Registry.</li>
      <li>For <tt>scope_revoke</tt>, <tt>scopes_revoked</tt> MUST be present
      and non-empty, and every entry MUST be an active synced AIP Scope
      Catalog scope or an accepted local/private extension scope that is
      currently granted by the target's effective Capability Manifest. Invalid
      scope entries MUST be rejected with <tt>invalid_scope</tt>. For all
      other revocation types, <tt>scopes_revoked</tt> MUST be absent.</li>
      <li>The Registry MUST construct the target authorization chain from its
      registration records. That chain consists of the target's root Principal
      DID and every ancestor AID recorded through the parent-child delegation
      index. For <tt>full_revoke</tt>, <tt>scope_revoke</tt>, and
      <tt>delegation_revoke</tt>, <tt>issued_by</tt> MUST equal either the
      target's root Principal DID or an ancestor AID in that chain. For
      <tt>principal_revoke</tt> targeting a Principal DID,
      <tt>issued_by</tt> MUST equal that Principal DID. For
      <tt>principal_revoke</tt> targeting an AID, <tt>issued_by</tt> MUST
      equal the target AID's root Principal DID. Unauthorized issuers MUST be
      rejected with <tt>revocation_unauthorized</tt>.</li>
      <li>For a DID issuer, <tt>kid</tt> MUST be a DID URL whose DID portion
      equals <tt>issued_by</tt>. The Registry MUST resolve the DID, locate the
      Ed25519 verification method named by <tt>kid</tt>, and verify the
      Revocation Object signature over the Section 5.7 signing input. For a
      <tt>did:aip</tt> issuer, the key lookup MUST use the authoritative
      Registry public-key endpoint for the referenced AID and key version. If
      the key cannot be resolved, is not Ed25519, is not controlled by
      <tt>issued_by</tt>, or the signature fails, the Registry MUST reject
      with <tt>revocation_invalid</tt>.</li>
    </ol>

    <t>
      Registry-generated Revocation Objects are not externally submitted
      through the public <tt>POST /v1/revocations</tt> endpoint. For
      <tt>parent_revoked</tt>, <tt>heartbeat_timeout</tt>, and
      <tt>lifecycle_expired</tt>, the Registry MUST set <tt>issued_by</tt> to
      its <tt>registry_id</tt>, set <tt>kid</tt> to a JWK listed in
      <tt>active_verification_keys.crl</tt> of the Registry Trust Record
      current at the Revocation Object <tt>timestamp</tt>, and sign the object
      with the corresponding private key.
    </t>

    <t>
      Acceptance MUST be atomic. On success, the Registry MUST store the
      Revocation Object immutably, update live revocation status, schedule CRL
      publication within the 15-minute freshness window defined in
      <xref target="crl"/>, and return HTTP 201 with
      <tt>Content-Type: application/json</tt> and the stored
      Revocation Object. If <tt>propagate_to_children</tt> is <tt>true</tt>,
      the Registry MUST recursively materialise child Revocation Objects with
      reason <tt>parent_revoked</tt> within 15 seconds. For
      <tt>principal_revoke</tt>, token invalidation does not depend on
      materialised child objects; propagation only adds audit and index
      records.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="crl" numbered="true">
  <name>Certificate Revocation List (CRL)</name>
    <t>
      The Registry MUST expose a canonical origin CRL endpoint at
      <tt>GET /v1/crl</tt> and MUST publish the preferred CRL retrieval URI
      as <tt>endpoints.crl</tt> in both <tt>/v1/registry-metadata</tt>
      and the signed Registry Trust Record. The published
      <tt>endpoints.crl</tt> value MAY be <tt>/v1/crl</tt> or an absolute
      HTTPS URI for a CDN or distributed object store. Relying Parties MUST
      retrieve CRL documents from the accepted Registry Trust Record's
      <tt>signed.endpoints.crl</tt> value rather than assuming
      <tt>registry_id + "/v1/crl"</tt>.
    </t>
    <t>
      The CRL MUST be updated within 15 minutes of a new Revocation
      Object being accepted. The published CRL retrieval URI MUST be served
      from a CDN or distributed infrastructure. CDN and object-store
      distribution is not a trust anchor: CRL documents MUST be signed by a
      JWK listed in
      <tt>active_verification_keys.crl</tt> of the Registry
      Trust Record version current at issuance time.
    </t>
    <t>
      The CRL is an AIP signed JSON document, not an X.509 CRL. A successful
      CRL response MUST use <tt>Content-Type: application/aip-crl+json</tt>
      and MUST conform to <tt>crl.schema.json</tt>. The top-level object MUST
      contain <tt>signed</tt> and <tt>signatures</tt>. The <tt>signed</tt>
      object MUST include <tt>registry_id</tt>, <tt>trust_record_version</tt>,
      <tt>crl_id</tt>, <tt>issued_at</tt>, <tt>next_update</tt>,
      <tt>sequence</tt>, <tt>publication_mode</tt>,
      <tt>revocation_count</tt>, and <tt>revocations</tt>. The
      <tt>publication_mode</tt> value MUST be <tt>"complete"</tt>,
      <tt>"index"</tt>, or <tt>"segment"</tt>. In <tt>"complete"</tt> mode,
      the <tt>revocations</tt> array contains the full signed Revocation
      Objects active for bounded-staleness validation at <tt>issued_at</tt>.
      In <tt>"index"</tt> mode, the <tt>revocations</tt> array MUST be empty
      and the signed object MUST contain <tt>segments</tt> as defined in
      <xref target="crl-response-registry"/>. In <tt>"segment"</tt> mode, the <tt>revocations</tt> array
      contains only the Revocation Objects assigned to that segment, and the
      signed object MUST contain <tt>segment_id</tt>.
    </t>
    <t>
      The CRL signing input is the RFC 8785 JSON Canonicalization Scheme (JCS)
      serialization of the <tt>signed</tt> object only. Each signature entry
      MUST contain <tt>keyid</tt> and <tt>sig</tt>. The <tt>keyid</tt> MUST
      match a JWK <tt>keyid</tt> in
      <tt>active_verification_keys.crl</tt> for the Registry Trust Record whose
      <tt>signed.version</tt> equals the CRL
      <tt>signed.trust_record_version</tt>. The signature algorithm is
      EdDSA over Ed25519. A Relying Party MUST reject an unsigned, malformed,
      or unverifiable CRL and MUST NOT treat CDN integrity, TLS termination, or
      object-store metadata as a substitute for this signature verification.
    </t>
    <t>
      CRL consumers MUST verify that <tt>signed.registry_id</tt> equals the
      accepted Registry Trust Record's <tt>signed.registry_id</tt>, that
      <tt>signed.trust_record_version</tt> identifies an accepted Registry
      Trust Record, and that at least one signature verifies under that trust
      record's <tt>active_verification_keys.crl</tt>. The
      <tt>next_update</tt> timestamp MUST be no later than 15 minutes after
      <tt>issued_at</tt>. Relying Parties MUST NOT use a CRL for new token
      validations after <tt>next_update</tt>; if no fresh verifiable CRL is
      available when one is required, validation MUST fail with
      <tt>registry_unavailable</tt>.
    </t>
    <t>
      CRL documents MUST include active <tt>principal_revoke</tt> entries by
      <tt>target_id</tt>. For Tier 1 validation, Relying Parties MUST check
      <tt>principal_revoke</tt> entries whose <tt>target_id</tt> equals the
      token's root Principal DID and entries whose <tt>target_id</tt> equals
      any AID in the token's validated <tt>aip_chain</tt>. A matching
      <tt>principal_revoke</tt> is equivalent to <tt>agent_revoked</tt> for
      that token.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="revocation-checking" numbered="true">
  <name>Revocation Checking</name>
    <t>
      A token's Tier is determined by its highest-risk
      scope. A token with one Tier 2 scope and any
      number of Tier 1 scopes is a Tier 2 token.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Tier 1 - Bounded-staleness:</strong> The Credential Token TTL is
      the effective catalog-derived TTL defined in <xref target="token-issuance"/>. Relying
      Parties validate revocation status at request validation time using a
      verifiable CRL whose <tt>next_update</tt> has not passed. A Relying Party
      MUST refresh its cached CRL before using it for new validations after
      <tt>next_update</tt>.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Tier 2 - Real-time revocation:</strong> Applies when the
      highest synced AIP Scope Catalog <tt>tier</tt> among requested scopes is
      2. Real-time Registry check on EVERY request. MUST NOT cache
      revocation status. DPoP MUST be verified for the request regardless of
      per-scope <tt>requires_dpop</tt> metadata. If Registry unreachable:
      MUST deny and return registry_unavailable.
    </t>
    <t>
      The live Tier 2 lookup uses
      <tt>GET /v1/agents/{aid}/revocation</tt>. A registered AID returns
      HTTP 200 whether or not it is revoked. The response body is the
      Revocation Status response defined in
      <xref target="agent-revocation-status-registry"/>. Unknown AIDs return
      <tt>unknown_aid</tt> (HTTP 404).
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Tier 3 - Enterprise:</strong> MUST use mTLS. MUST support
      OCSP per RFC 6960. Tier 3 supplements, not replaces,
      Tier 2.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Child Agent Propagation:</strong> When the
      Registry processes a Revocation Object with
      propagate_to_children: true, the Registry MUST
      recursively revoke descendants within 15 seconds.
      A <tt>principal_revoke</tt> invalidates dependent tokens regardless of
      this flag; propagation only controls whether descendant Revocation
      Objects are written for indexing, CRL compactness, and auditability.
    </t>

    <t>
      Replica Registries MUST synchronise within 45 seconds.
      Combined end-to-end propagation MUST NOT exceed
      60 seconds.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Approval Envelope interaction:</strong> When an
      agent AID is revoked, the Registry MUST transition
      all Approval Envelopes in pending_approval, approved,
      or executing status to failed. Unclaimed steps
      for that actor MUST be marked failed. In-progress
      claims MUST be treated as failed; the Registry
      MUST initiate compensation if applicable.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="rpnp" numbered="true">
  <name>Registry Push Notification Protocol (RPNP)</name>
    <t>
      RPNP is an OPTIONAL Registry capability for real-time
      revocation event delivery.
    </t>

    <section anchor="rpnp-overview" numbered="true">
  <name>Overview</name>
      <t>
        When RPNP is implemented:
      </t>

      <ul>
        <li>Registry MUST start the first push delivery attempt within 5 seconds of the event commit time defined in <xref target="rpnp-delivery"/></li>
        <li>Push payloads MUST be signed by a JWK listed in <tt>active_verification_keys.notifications</tt> of the Registry Trust Record version current at issuance time</li>
        <li>Subscriber authentication MUST be verified at subscription time</li>
      </ul>

      <t>
        For subscribing Relying Parties, the effective revocation
        notification window is the RPNP first-attempt latency (at most 5 seconds)
        rather than the CRL refresh interval. RPNP does not
        replace CRL; it supplements it. Confirmed delivery depends on
        subscriber availability and the retry rules in <xref target="rpnp-delivery"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rpnp-subscription" numbered="true">
  <name>Subscription</name>
      <t>
        A Relying Party subscribes by calling POST /v1/subscriptions:
      </t>
      <t>
        The request body MUST conform to the
        <tt>subscription_request</tt> definition in
        <tt>rpnp.schema.json</tt>. On success, the Registry assigns a
        <tt>subscription_id</tt> with the pattern
        <tt>sub:&lt;uuid-v4&gt;</tt> and returns HTTP 201 with a body
        conforming to the <tt>subscription_response</tt> definition in
        <tt>rpnp.schema.json</tt>.
      </t>

                        <table>
              <name>Subscription Fields</name>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left">Field</th>
                  <th align="center">Required</th>
                  <th align="left">Constraints</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>subscriber_did</td>
                  <td>REQUIRED</td>
                  <td>MUST be did:web or did:aip</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>event_types</td>
                  <td>REQUIRED</td>
                  <td>Array containing one or more of <tt>full_revoke</tt>, <tt>scope_revoke</tt>, <tt>delegation_revoke</tt>, <tt>principal_revoke</tt>, and <tt>engagement_cancelled</tt></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>scope_filter</td>
                  <td>REQUIRED</td>
                  <td>aid, principal, or all</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>targets</td>
                  <td>CONDITIONAL</td>
                  <td>REQUIRED when scope_filter is aid or principal</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>webhook_uri</td>
                  <td>REQUIRED</td>
                  <td>HTTPS URI</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>hmac_secret</td>
                  <td>REQUIRED</td>
                  <td>Base64url-encoded shared secret; minimum 32 bytes of entropy</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>subscription_expires_at</td>
                  <td>REQUIRED</td>
                  <td>ISO 8601 UTC; max 90 days</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

      <t>
        The subscription request MUST be authenticated via DPoP proof bound
        to <tt>subscriber_did</tt>. A DPoP proof that only proves possession
        of an arbitrary key is not sufficient subscription authentication.
        If the DPoP proof is absent, malformed, unverifiable, replayed,
        not bound to <tt>subscriber_did</tt>, or not bound to the current
        request target, the Registry MUST reject with
        <tt>subscription_auth_required</tt>.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Registry MUST accept exactly the following RPNP subscription
        authentication profiles:
      </t>
      <ol type="%d">
        <li>
          <t><strong>DID-bound DPoP:</strong> The DPoP proof protected header
          MUST contain a public verification key and a DID URL key identifier
          in <tt>jwk.kid</tt>. The DID portion of <tt>jwk.kid</tt> MUST equal
          <tt>subscriber_did</tt>. The Registry MUST resolve
          <tt>subscriber_did</tt> and verify that <tt>jwk.kid</tt> identifies
          an Ed25519 verification method controlled by that DID. For
          <tt>did:web</tt>, resolution uses the DID method's normal DID
          Document resolution. For <tt>did:aip</tt>, resolution uses the
          authoritative AIP Registry public-key endpoint for the referenced
          AID and key identifier. The public key in the DPoP header MUST be
          byte-for-byte equivalent to the resolved verification method, and
          the DPoP proof signature MUST verify under that key.</t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t><strong>Authorization-bound DPoP:</strong> The request MAY
          include <tt>Authorization: DPoP &lt;token&gt;</tt>. In that case,
          the Registry MUST validate the token using Section 9 with the
          subscription endpoint as the audience, MUST validate the DPoP proof
          using Section 9 Step 10 including the <tt>ath</tt> check, and MUST
          verify that the token issuer, token subject, and leaf
          <tt>aip_chain</tt> subject all equal <tt>subscriber_did</tt>. This
          profile is available only when <tt>subscriber_did</tt> is a
          <tt>did:aip</tt> AID.</t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>
        For either profile, the Registry MUST verify <tt>htm</tt>,
        <tt>htu</tt>, <tt>iat</tt>, and <tt>jti</tt> replay state using the
        DPoP validation rules in Section 9 Step 10. In DID-bound DPoP without
        an <tt>Authorization</tt> header, the <tt>ath</tt> claim MUST be
        absent. If an <tt>Authorization</tt> header is present, <tt>ath</tt>
        MUST be present and valid for that exact token.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Registry MUST authorize the requested <tt>scope_filter</tt>
        against the authenticated <tt>subscriber_did</tt>. If
        <tt>scope_filter</tt> is <tt>"all"</tt> and the subscriber is not
        explicitly authorized by Registry policy for global revocation
        notifications, the Registry MUST reject the request with
        <tt>subscription_scope_forbidden</tt>. If <tt>scope_filter</tt> is
        <tt>"aid"</tt> or <tt>"principal"</tt>, every value in
        <tt>targets</tt> MUST be within the subscriber's authorized
        observation set; otherwise, the Registry MUST reject with
        <tt>subscription_scope_forbidden</tt>.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Registry MUST enforce configured per-subscriber and global active
        subscription quotas before accepting a new subscription. If accepting
        the request would exceed any applicable quota, the Registry MUST
        reject with <tt>subscription_limit_exceeded</tt>. The Registry SHOULD
        include <tt>Retry-After</tt> when quota exhaustion is temporary.
      </t>
      <t>
        The <tt>hmac_secret</tt> value is shared secret material used by the
        Registry to authenticate push event delivery. The value MUST be
        transmitted only over TLS. The Registry MUST retain the secret, or a
        reversibly encrypted form of the secret, for the lifetime of the
        subscription so it can compute delivery HMACs. A Registry MUST NOT
        store only a one-way hash of this value while the subscription remains
        active. Registries MAY additionally store a hash of the secret for
        audit or lookup purposes, but that hash is not sufficient to sign
        delivery requests.
      </t>
      <t>
        <tt>GET /v1/subscriptions/{id}</tt> MUST return the current
        <tt>subscription_response</tt> object. The <tt>status</tt> field MUST
        be one of <tt>active</tt>, <tt>degraded</tt>, <tt>cancelled</tt>, or
        <tt>expired</tt>. Status responses MUST include
        <tt>consecutive_failures</tt>, <tt>last_delivery_attempt_at</tt>,
        <tt>last_success_at</tt>, <tt>next_retry_at</tt>, and
        <tt>last_delivery_status</tt>, using null for timestamp fields that
        have not yet occurred. <tt>DELETE /v1/subscriptions/{id}</tt> MUST
        atomically transition an active or degraded subscription to
        <tt>cancelled</tt> and return the updated
        <tt>subscription_response</tt>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rpnp-payload" numbered="true">
  <name>Push Event Payload</name>
      <t>
        Push events are delivered as HTTP POST to the subscriber's
        webhook_uri. The body is a compact-serialised JWT signed
        by a JWK listed in
        <tt>active_verification_keys.notifications</tt> of the
        Registry Trust Record version current at issuance time.
      </t>

                        <table>
              <name>RPNP JWT Fields</name>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left">Header Field</th>
                  <th align="left">Value</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>typ</td>
                  <td>AIP-RPNP+JWT</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>alg</td>
                  <td>EdDSA</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>kid</td>
                  <td>Registry notification key ID</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>aip_trv</td>
                  <td>Integer Registry Trust Record version whose <tt>active_verification_keys.notifications</tt> contains <tt>kid</tt></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

      <t>
        The protected <tt>aip_trv</tt> header is used to select an already
        pinned Registry Trust Record for the event issuer. Subscribers MUST
        NOT fetch new trust state during push-event validation to establish
        trust for that event.
      </t>

                        <table>
              <name>RPNP Payload Fields</name>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th align="left">Payload Field</th>
                  <th align="left">Description</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>iss</td>
                  <td>Registry ID</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>sub</td>
                  <td>Affected AID or engagement ID</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>iat</td>
                  <td>Unix timestamp</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>exp</td>
                  <td>Unix timestamp; MUST be no more than 300 seconds after iat</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>jti</td>
                  <td>UUID v4; unique event ID</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>subscription_id</td>
                  <td>Subscription identifier receiving this push event</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>event_type</td>
                  <td>One of subscribed types</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>event_data</td>
                  <td>Event-specific data</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

      <t>
        The JWT payload MUST conform to the <tt>push_payload</tt> definition
        in <tt>rpnp.schema.json</tt>. The request MUST include an
        <tt>X-AIP-Signature</tt> header using this exact syntax:
      </t>
      <artwork type="text"><![CDATA[
X-AIP-Signature: <sig-header>

sig-header = "v1;t=" timestamp ";kid=" subscription-id ";h=" hmac
      ]]></artwork>
      <t>
        The HMAC input is the ASCII decimal <tt>t</tt> value, followed by a
        period (<tt>.</tt>), followed by the exact request body octets. The
        <tt>h</tt> value is <tt>BASE64URL(HMAC-SHA256(hmac_secret, input))</tt>
        without padding. The <tt>kid</tt> value MUST equal the JWT
        <tt>subscription_id</tt>. The subscriber MUST verify the Registry JWT
        signature, the HMAC, and the subscription binding before accepting the
        event.
      </t>
      <t>
        Subscribers MUST reject a push event if the header timestamp
        <tt>t</tt> is more than 300 seconds from the subscriber's current
        clock, if the JWT <tt>exp</tt> is in the past, if <tt>exp - iat</tt>
        exceeds 300 seconds, or if the <tt>jti</tt> has already been accepted
        for the same <tt>subscription_id</tt>. Subscribers MUST retain replay
        state keyed by <tt>(subscription_id, jti)</tt> at least until the
        later of the JWT <tt>exp</tt> time and 300 seconds after receipt.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rpnp-delivery" numbered="true">
  <name>Delivery Guarantees</name>
      <t>
        RPNP provides at-least-once best-effort push delivery. It does not
        provide exactly-once delivery, and subscribers MUST use the
        <tt>jti</tt> replay rules in this section to make event processing
        idempotent.
      </t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          The Registry MUST record an <tt>event_committed_at</tt> instant
          using its reliable UTC clock when the state transition that creates
          the push event is durably committed. For revocation events, this is
          the instant at which the Revocation Object is accepted and live
          revocation status is committed. For engagement cancellation events,
          this is the instant at which the cancellation state transition is
          committed.
        </li>
        <li>
          The Registry MUST start the first HTTPS POST delivery attempt to
          each active matching subscription no later than 5 seconds after
          <tt>event_committed_at</tt>. The interval ends when the Registry
          begins sending the request to the subscriber's
          <tt>webhook_uri</tt>. This 5-second requirement applies to the first
          delivery attempt, not to confirmed successful receipt.
        </li>
        <li>
          The Registry MUST set <tt>last_delivery_attempt_at</tt> to the
          Registry UTC time at which each delivery attempt begins. If the first
          attempt starts more than 5 seconds after
          <tt>event_committed_at</tt>, the Registry MUST record
          <tt>last_delivery_status</tt> as
          <tt>first_attempt_sla_missed</tt> until a later delivery attempt
          overwrites it with a more recent status.
        </li>
        <li>
          On delivery failure, meaning timeout or any non-2xx HTTP response,
          the Registry MUST perform at least three retry attempts after the
          initial delivery attempt, using exponential backoff intervals of 1s,
          2s, and 4s as the minimum retry schedule. The Registry MAY add jitter
          or continue retrying after those attempts, but MUST NOT schedule the
          first three retries later than those intervals unless the subscription
          has expired or been cancelled.
        </li>
        <li>
          A delivery attempt MUST be treated as timed out if the subscriber
          does not return a final HTTP response within 5 seconds after the
          Registry finishes sending the request body, unless the Registry
          applies a shorter deployment-profile timeout.
        </li>
        <li>
          After 3 consecutive failures, mark the subscription
          <tt>degraded</tt>, update <tt>consecutive_failures</tt>,
          <tt>last_delivery_attempt_at</tt>, <tt>last_delivery_status</tt>,
          and <tt>next_retry_at</tt>, and continue to make the event available
          through CRL or live revocation status. Subscribers MUST fall back to
          CRL or live Registry checks while the subscription is degraded.
        </li>
        <li>On any successful 2xx delivery, reset
          <tt>consecutive_failures</tt> to 0, set
          <tt>last_success_at</tt>, clear <tt>next_retry_at</tt>, and restore
          <tt>status</tt> to <tt>active</tt> unless the subscription has
          expired or been cancelled.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
