<section anchor="principal-grant" numbered="true">
  <name>Principal Grant Ceremony (AIP-GRANT)</name>
  <t>
    The AIP-GRANT ceremony provides a standardised protocol for principals
    to authorise AI agents. AIP-GRANT is analogous to the OAuth 2.0
    Authorization Code Flow <xref target="RFC6749"/>, adapted for the agent
    identity use case.
    Two independent implementations following this section MUST
    produce interoperable grant interactions.
  </t>

  <section anchor="grant-overview" numbered="true">
  <name>Overview and Roles</name>
    <t>
      The AIP-GRANT ceremony involves three actors:
    </t>

    <dl>
      <dt>Agent Deployer</dt>
      <dd>
        The party that constructs the GrantRequest and submits the
        Registration Envelope to the Registry. The deployer generates
        the agent's Ed25519 keypair before initiating the grant
        and may be the principal themselves or a service acting
        on the principal's behalf.
      </dd>

      <dt>Principal Wallet</dt>
      <dd>
        Software that holds the principal's DID private key and executes
        the signing ceremony. The Principal Wallet MUST verify the deployer's
        signature and MUST obtain explicit human approval before signing.
      </dd>

      <dt>AIP Registry</dt>
      <dd>
        The service that accepts the Registration Envelope. The Registry's
        role is defined in <xref target="registry"/>; it is not modified
        by AIP-GRANT.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <t>
      The basic flow:
    </t>

    <artwork type="example"><![CDATA[
   Agent Deployer      Principal Wallet      AIP Registry
         |                     |                  |
         |-- GrantRequest ---->|                  |
         | (agent_aid,         |                  |
         |  capabilities,      |                  |
         |  purpose, nonce)    |                  |
         |                     |                  |
         |             [Display consent UI]       |
         |           [Human reviews & signs]      |
         |                     |                  |
         |<-- GrantResponse ---|                  |
         | (signed             |                  |
         |  PrincipalToken)    |                  |
         |                     |                  |
         |-- Registration Envelope -------------->|
         | (identity + manifest +                 |
         |  principal_token)                      |
         |                                        |
         |<-- AID --------------------------------|
]]></artwork>
  </section>

  <section anchor="grant-request" numbered="true">
  <name>GrantRequest Object</name>
    <t>
      The GrantRequest is a JSON object constructed by the Agent Deployer.
      It MUST be signed by the deployer's Ed25519 key when transmitted
      over the Web Redirect or QR Code bindings. For G2, the signed
      request MUST identify the deployer through the <tt>deployer_did</tt>
      field and the signature key MUST be bound to that DID. The nonce MUST be
      cryptographically random and MUST contain at least 128 bits of
      entropy.
    </t>
    <t>
      The request MUST also include <tt>deployer_name</tt> for consent UI
      display. The <tt>deployer_name</tt> value is human-readable metadata
      only; it is not a trust anchor and MUST NOT replace verification of
      <tt>deployer_did</tt> and the signed GrantRequest envelope.
    </t>

    <t><strong>GrantRequest Fields:</strong></t>

    <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
                  <dt><tt>grant_request_id</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>pattern: gr:&lt;UUIDv4-lowerhex&gt;</dd>


                  <dt><tt>aip_version</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>AIP protocol compatibility version; MUST be "0.3"; not the Internet-Draft revision</dd>


                  <dt><tt>agent_aid</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>MUST match did:aip ABNF; pre-derived AID of the agent being authorised; Principal Token sub MUST equal this value</dd>


                  <dt><tt>agent_name</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>maxLength: 64; displayed in consent UI</dd>


                  <dt><tt>agent_type</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>registered namespace value</dd>


                  <dt><tt>model.provider</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>displayed in consent UI</dd>


                  <dt><tt>model.model_id</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>displayed in consent UI</dd>


                  <dt><tt>requested_capabilities</tt> (object; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>Capability Manifest capabilities sub-schema</dd>


                  <dt><tt>purpose</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>minLength: 1; maxLength: 512</dd>


                  <dt><tt>delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt> (integer; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>requested maximum delegation lifetime; min: 300; max: 31536000; approved value MUST NOT exceed this value</dd>


                  <dt><tt>nonce</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>minLength: 22; cryptographically random</dd>


                  <dt><tt>request_expires_at</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>ISO 8601 UTC</dd>


                  <dt><tt>callback_uri</tt> (string; CONDITIONAL)</dt>


                  <dd>REQUIRED for Web Redirect and G3 OAuth authorization requests; MUST use HTTPS; for G3, MUST equal the OAuth redirect_uri</dd>


                  <dt><tt>state</tt> (string; CONDITIONAL)</dt>


                  <dd>REQUIRED for G3 OAuth authorization requests; echoed unchanged and MUST equal the OAuth state parameter</dd>


                  <dt><tt>deployer_did</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>W3C DID of the deployer; used to verify signed GrantRequests and displayed in consent UI</dd>


                  <dt><tt>deployer_name</tt> (string; REQUIRED)</dt>


                  <dd>minLength: 1; maxLength: 128; displayed alongside deployer_did; display metadata only, not a trust anchor</dd>


                  <dt><tt>deployer_public_key</tt> (object; OPTIONAL)</dt>


                  <dd>JWK key hint only; MUST match the verification method resolved from deployer_did and MUST NOT replace DID resolution</dd>


                </dl>

    <t>
      The deployer MUST generate the agent's AID before constructing
      the GrantRequest and MUST include that value as <tt>agent_aid</tt>.
      The Principal Token produced from this grant MUST use the original
      GrantRequest <tt>agent_aid</tt> as its <tt>sub</tt> claim.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Signed GrantRequest envelope:</strong> A GrantRequest sent
      directly to a Principal Wallet using the Web Redirect or QR Code
      binding MUST be carried as a compact JWS whose payload is the UTF-8
      JSON serialization of the GrantRequest object. The protected JWS
      header MUST contain <tt>typ</tt> equal to
      <tt>"aip-grant+jws"</tt>, <tt>alg</tt> equal to
      <tt>"EdDSA"</tt>, and <tt>kid</tt> as a DID URL. The DID portion of
      <tt>kid</tt> MUST equal the GrantRequest <tt>deployer_did</tt>. The
      referenced verification method MUST resolve from the
      <tt>deployer_did</tt> DID Document, MUST be controlled by
      <tt>deployer_did</tt>, and MUST be an Ed25519 signing key. If
      <tt>deployer_public_key</tt> is present, it is a cache hint only; the
      Principal Wallet MUST verify that it is byte-for-byte equivalent to
      the resolved verification method before using it and MUST NOT trust a
      self-supplied key that is not present in the resolved DID Document.
    </t>
    <t>
      The same signed GrantRequest envelope format is used by the G3 OAuth
      binding. In that case, the compact JWS is carried in the
      <tt>aip_grant_request</tt> authorization request parameter and is
      verified by the Registry acting as OAuth Authorization Server before
      any authentication or consent ceremony is started.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="grant-consent" numbered="true">
  <name>Principal Wallet Consent Requirements</name>
    <t>
      The Principal Wallet MUST implement the following requirements
      before signing any grant.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Nonce and expiry checks:</strong> The Principal Wallet
      MUST check request_expires_at against the current clock. If expired,
      it MUST reject with grant_request_expired and MUST NOT show the
      consent UI. The Principal Wallet MUST maintain a record of seen
      grant_request_id values for at least 30 days and MUST reject
      replays with grant_request_replayed.
    </t>
    <t>
      The Principal Wallet MUST use its own reliable UTC clock for
      <tt>request_expires_at</tt> checks and MAY allow a 30-second clock
      skew tolerance. If the Principal Wallet's current time is more than 30
      seconds after <tt>request_expires_at</tt>, the request is expired. If
      the Principal Wallet cannot determine reliable current UTC time, it MUST reject
      with <tt>grant_request_invalid</tt> rather than issuing a back-dated
      or future-dated Principal Token.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Signed request checks:</strong> For a G2 GrantRequest, the
      Principal Wallet MUST verify the signed GrantRequest envelope before
      displaying the consent UI. The Principal Wallet MUST reject with
      <tt>grant_request_invalid</tt> and MUST NOT show the consent UI if
      the request is unsigned, if <tt>deployer_did</tt> is absent, if the
      JWS <tt>kid</tt> DID does not equal <tt>deployer_did</tt>, if the
      deployer DID cannot be resolved, if the referenced key is not an
      Ed25519 signing key controlled by <tt>deployer_did</tt>, or if the
      JWS signature verification fails.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Mandatory display elements:</strong> The consent UI
      MUST display ALL of the following before presenting the
      sign/decline choice:
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>Agent name (agent_name) and type (agent_type)</li>
      <li>AI model - provider and model_id</li>
      <li>Purpose - the purpose field verbatim</li>
      <li>Deployer identity - deployer_name and deployer_did</li>
      <li>All requested capabilities using trusted AIP Scope Catalog display metadata</li>
      <li>Delegation validity - requested duration and the approximate expiry computed from delegation_valid_for_seconds using the Principal Wallet's current UTC clock</li>
        <li><strong>Destructive Operations:</strong> Any scope whose active
        AIP Scope Catalog entry has <tt>destructive: true</tt> MUST be
        highlighted in the UI using the mandatory two-step confirmation flow
        required for Principal Wallet conformance in
        <xref target="conformance-classes"/>.</li>
    </ol>

    <t>
      Before displaying the consent UI, the Principal Wallet MUST resolve
      <tt>requested_capabilities</tt> to the concrete requested scope
      identifiers using the scope-to-capability rules in
      <xref target="field-constraints"/> and any explicit private extension
      policy accepted by the Principal Wallet. The Principal Wallet MUST use a trusted immutable
      AIP Scope Catalog Snapshot for this resolution. For each requested
      scope, the Principal Wallet MUST find an <tt>active</tt> or
      <tt>experimental</tt> scope entry and MUST find complete trusted
      <tt>display</tt> metadata for the Principal Wallet's selected locale or for the
      entry's <tt>display.default_locale</tt>. If no trusted catalog snapshot
      is available, if a requested capability cannot be resolved to a
      concrete scope identifier, if the scope entry is unknown, removed,
      reserved, or outside an accepted private extension policy, or if the
      required display metadata is absent or incomplete, the Principal Wallet MUST
      reject with <tt>grant_request_invalid</tt> and MUST NOT show the
      consent UI.
    </t>

    <t>
      The Principal Wallet MUST NOT synthesize consent text from raw scope
      identifiers, capability field names, deployer-supplied display strings,
      generic family names, or untrusted catalog data. The title value in
      <tt>display.strings[locale].title</tt> is the canonical
      human-readable capability string for that locale. The Principal Wallet MAY also
      display <tt>display.strings[locale].summary</tt>, but it MUST NOT use
      the summary to replace or weaken required destructive-operation
      highlighting.
    </t>

    <t>
      If an issued Principal Token includes a <tt>purpose</tt> claim, the
      claim value MUST be either the exact GrantRequest <tt>purpose</tt>
      value or a shorter summary that was displayed to and approved by the
      principal before signing. A Principal Token issuer MUST NOT include a
      deployer-supplied or issuer-generated <tt>purpose</tt> claim that was
      not presented during consent.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Principal Token signing profile:</strong> For a root Principal
      Token, the token issuer is always the root principal identified by
      <tt>principal.id</tt>. A Principal Wallet or other principal-controlled
      signing component that constructs a root Principal Token after consent
      MUST sign the JWT with EdDSA, MUST set <tt>iss</tt> to
      <tt>principal.id</tt>, and MUST use a JOSE header <tt>kid</tt>
      identifying an Ed25519 verification method controlled by
      <tt>principal.id</tt>. A Registry or authorization server MAY prepare
      the payload, mediate consent, collect high-assurance authentication
      context, store the GrantResponse, or deliver the signed token, but it
      MUST NOT sign a root Principal Token with a Registry-controlled or
      authorization-server-controlled key and MUST NOT set <tt>iss</tt> to
      the Registry or authorization server. The Principal Token payload
      <tt>sub</tt> claim MUST equal the <tt>agent_aid</tt> value from the
      original GrantRequest. A service that cannot obtain a
      principal-controlled Ed25519 signature MUST NOT issue a root Principal
      Token with that principal as <tt>iss</tt>.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>Delegation expiry derivation:</strong> The Principal Token
      issuer MUST compute a single issuance timestamp from its current
      reliable UTC clock at the moment of signing. It MUST set the Principal
      Token <tt>issued_at</tt> claim and the GrantResponse
      <tt>signed_at</tt> field to that same instant. The approved delegation
      lifetime MUST be represented as
      <tt>approved_delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt>, MUST be at least 300
      seconds, and MUST NOT exceed the original GrantRequest
      <tt>delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt>. The issuer MAY approve a
      shorter lifetime than requested.
    </t>
    <t>
      The Principal Token <tt>expires_at</tt> claim MUST equal
      <tt>issued_at</tt> plus
      <tt>approved_delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt> seconds. No clock skew
      tolerance is applied to this calculation; clock skew tolerance applies
      only when validators compare timestamps to their local current time.
      The issuer MUST NOT use the deployer's clock, callback receipt time, or
      <tt>request_expires_at</tt> as the Principal Token <tt>issued_at</tt>
      value.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Draft-02 Catalog display metadata:</strong>
    </t>

    <t>
      The AIP Scope Catalog is the normative source of capability display
      metadata. Each scope entry's <tt>display</tt> member is defined in
      <xref target="scope-map-registry"/>. For standard Draft-02 scopes,
      <tt>display.strings["en-US"].title</tt> MUST equal the display string
      listed below. The corresponding <tt>summary</tt> value MUST be
      non-empty and MUST describe the same capability without broadening the
      authorization represented by the scope. Extension and private scopes
      MUST provide equivalent catalog display metadata through their catalog
      entry or accepted private extension policy before a Principal Wallet can present
      consent for them.
    </t>

                <table>
          <name>Draft-02 Standard Scope Display Titles</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Scope</th>
              <th align="left">Display String</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>email.read</td>
              <td>Read your email messages and metadata</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>email.write</td>
              <td>Create and draft email messages</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>email.send</td>
              <td>Send email on your behalf</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>email.delete</td>
              <td>Permanently delete your email messages - this cannot be undone</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>calendar.read</td>
              <td>Read your calendar events</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>calendar.write</td>
              <td>Create and update calendar events</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>calendar.delete</td>
              <td>Delete your calendar events</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filesystem.read</td>
              <td>Read files from your local storage</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filesystem.write</td>
              <td>Save and modify files on your local storage</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filesystem.execute</td>
              <td>Execute scripts and commands on your system - HIGH RISK</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>filesystem.delete</td>
              <td>Delete files from your local storage</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>web.browse</td>
              <td>Browse the web and read website content</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>web.forms_submit</td>
              <td>Submit data to web forms</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>web.download</td>
              <td>Download files from the web to your system</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>transactions</td>
              <td>Make financial transactions up to specified limits</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>communicate.whatsapp</td>
              <td>Send and receive messages via WhatsApp</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>communicate.telegram</td>
              <td>Send and receive messages via Telegram</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>communicate.sms</td>
              <td>Send and receive SMS messages</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>communicate.voice</td>
              <td>Initiate and receive voice calls</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>spawn_agents.create</td>
              <td>Create child AI agents on your behalf</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>spawn_agents.manage</td>
              <td>Monitor and manage your existing child agents</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
  </section>

  <section anchor="grant-response" numbered="true">
  <name>GrantResponse Object</name>
    <t>
      The GrantResponse is constructed and signed by the Principal Wallet
      after the principal approves, partially approves, or declines the
      signing ceremony.
    </t>

                <table>
          <name>GrantResponse Fields</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Field</th>
              <th align="center">Required</th>
              <th align="left">Constraints</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>grant_request_id</td>
              <td>REQUIRED</td>
              <td>MUST match original request</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>nonce</td>
              <td>REQUIRED</td>
              <td>MUST match original nonce</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>status</td>
              <td>REQUIRED</td>
              <td>enum: "approved", "rejected", "partial"</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>principal_id</td>
              <td>REQUIRED</td>
              <td>W3C DID of signing principal</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>principal_token</td>
              <td>CONDITIONAL</td>
              <td>REQUIRED when status is "approved" or "partial"</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>signed_at</td>
              <td>REQUIRED</td>
              <td>ISO 8601 UTC; same instant as Principal Token issued_at when principal_token is present</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

    <t>
      A GrantResponse with status "approved" or "partial" MUST also include
      <tt>approved_delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt>. The value MUST be an
      integer from 300 through the original GrantRequest
      <tt>delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt>, inclusive, and is used to derive
      the Principal Token <tt>expires_at</tt> claim.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Deployer validation of GrantResponse:</strong> Upon receipt the deployer
      MUST:
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>Verify grant_request_id matches the original request</li>
      <li>Verify nonce matches. If mismatch, the deployer MUST reject the
      GrantResponse with <tt>grant_nonce_mismatch</tt>; the mismatch MUST be
      treated as a forgery attempt and no agent is registered.</li>
      <li>If status is "rejected", the deployer MUST treat the grant as a
      terminal failure with <tt>grant_rejected_by_principal</tt> and no agent
      is registered.</li>
      <li>Verify <tt>approved_delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt> is present
      for "approved" or "partial" responses, is at least 300 seconds, and
      does not exceed the original GrantRequest
      <tt>delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt></li>
      <li>Decode and verify the principal_token JWT signature</li>
      <li>Verify the principal_token payload sub exactly matches
      <tt>agent_aid</tt> from the original GrantRequest</li>
      <li>Verify the principal_token payload <tt>issued_at</tt> represents
      the same instant as the GrantResponse <tt>signed_at</tt></li>
      <li>Verify <tt>signed_at</tt> and <tt>issued_at</tt> are not more than
      30 seconds in the future relative to the deployer's current UTC clock,
      and that <tt>signed_at</tt> is not more than 24 hours in the past</li>
      <li>Verify the principal_token payload <tt>expires_at</tt> equals
      <tt>issued_at</tt> plus
      <tt>approved_delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt> seconds</li>
    </ol>
    <t>
      If any GrantResponse validation check fails, the deployer MUST treat
      the GrantResponse as invalid and MUST NOT submit a Registration
      Envelope based on it.
    </t>
    <t>
      When a deployer, Registry, Principal Wallet, or authorization server returns an
      AIP error response for a rejected grant, the error code MUST be
      <tt>grant_rejected_by_principal</tt>. When it returns an AIP error
      response for a GrantResponse whose <tt>nonce</tt> does not match the
      original GrantRequest, the error code MUST be
      <tt>grant_nonce_mismatch</tt>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="grant-transport" numbered="true">
  <name>Transport Bindings</name>
    <t>
      Implementations MUST support the Web Redirect Flow.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Web Redirect Flow:</strong>
    </t>

    <artwork type="example"><![CDATA[
https://wallet.example.com/aip-grant
  ?request=<compact-JWS-signed-GrantRequest>
  &aip_version=0.3
]]></artwork>

    <t>
      After the principal signs, the Principal Wallet delivers the GrantResponse:
    </t>

    <artwork type="example"><![CDATA[
POST <callback_uri>
Content-Type: application/json

{GrantResponse JSON}
]]></artwork>

    <t>
      The callback_uri MUST be pre-registered by the deployer.
      Principal Wallets MUST NOT deliver GrantResponses to unregistered URIs.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="sub-agent-delegation" numbered="true">
  <name>Sub-Agent Delegation Flow</name>
    <t>
      When a parent agent delegates to a child agent, the parent acts as
      the delegation issuer for the child. No new human consent UI is
      required, because the parent can only delegate scopes and constraints
      that are already within its own accepted authority.
    </t>
    <t>
      The child is registered with a delegated Principal Token, not a second
      root Principal Token. The delegated token's <tt>sub</tt> is the child
      AID, <tt>delegated_by</tt> is the parent AID, and
      <tt>delegation_depth</tt> is the parent's depth plus one. The Registry
      validates the submitted Registration Envelope using Registration Check 9
      and stores the reconstructed parent-plus-child chain for later runtime
      validation.
    </t>

    <t>
      The parent agent MUST:
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>Verify requested child capabilities are a strict subset of its own
        Capability Manifest (Rule D-1)</li>
      <li>Generate a fresh Ed25519 keypair for the child agent</li>
      <li>Construct and sign the child's Principal Token</li>
      <li>Construct the Registration Envelope for the child</li>
      <li>Submit the Registration Envelope to the Registry</li>
      <li>Provision the child's private key through a secure channel</li>
    </ol>

    <t>
      The parent MUST NOT retain the child's private key after
      successful provisioning. Retaining the child's private key enables
      the parent to forge Credential Tokens in the child's name and
      constitutes a violation of the principle of least privilege.
      This is a local implementation conformance and key-management
      requirement. The Registry and Relying Parties cannot determine from
      protocol messages whether the parent retained a copy of the child's
      private key, and MUST NOT treat private-key deletion as a Registry
      acceptance check or Credential Token validation precondition.
      Deployment profiles that audit this requirement MUST collect the
      sub-agent provisioning and deletion evidence defined in
      <xref target="key-management"/>.
    </t>

    <t>
      For sub-agent delegation, a parent agent MAY include a <tt>purpose</tt>
      claim in the child's Principal Token to describe the delegated work.
      That claim is signed audit metadata only. It MUST NOT expand the child
      agent's scopes or constraints and MUST NOT be treated by Relying
      Parties as a substitute for Capability Manifest or Approval Envelope
      validation.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="grant-errors" numbered="true">
  <name>AIP-GRANT Error Codes</name>
                <table>
          <name>AIP-GRANT Error Codes</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Code</th>
              <th align="left">Description</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>grant_request_expired</td>
              <td>request_expires_at has passed</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>grant_request_replayed</td>
              <td>grant_request_id seen before</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>grant_request_invalid</td>
              <td>GrantRequest malformed or signature failed</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>grant_rejected_by_principal</td>
              <td>Principal declined the grant</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>grant_nonce_mismatch</td>
              <td>GrantResponse nonce does not match</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
  </section>

  <section anchor="g1-grant" numbered="true">
  <name>G1: Registry-Mediated Grant Flow</name>
    <t>
      The G1 (Registry-Mediated) grant profile is designed for consumer
      deployments where the agent deployer does not operate its own
      Principal Wallet integration. The AIP Registry brokers the
      consent ceremony on the deployer's behalf.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Actors:</strong> Agent Deployer, AIP Registry, Principal
      (via Registry-hosted or redirected Principal Wallet consent UI).
    </t>

    <artwork type="example"><![CDATA[
      Deployer               Registry              Principal
         |                      |                      |
         |-- POST /v1/grants -->|                      |
         |  (GrantRequest +     |                      |
         |   callback_uri)      |                      |
         |<-- 201 grant_id + ---|                      |
         |    wallet_redirect   |                      |
         |                      |                      |
         |-- [redirect principal to Principal Wallet URI] ------>|
         |                      |                      |
         |                      |<--- authenticates ---|
         |                      |<-- approve/decline --|
         |                      |                      |
         | [Principal-controlled signer signs token]   |
         |                      |                      |
         |<--- POST callback ---|                      |
         |    (GrantResponse)   |                      |
         |                      |                      |
         |-- GET /v1/grants/id->|                      |
         |<--- GrantResponse ---|                      |
]]></artwork>

    <t>
      <strong>Step-by-step definition:</strong>
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>
        The deployer generates the agent's Ed25519 keypair and constructs
        a GrantRequest. For G1, callback_uri is REQUIRED.
      </li>
      <li>The deployer calls POST /v1/grants. See example response.</li>
      <li>
        The deployer redirects the principal to wallet_redirect_uri.
        The Registry presents a consent UI.
      </li>
      <li>
        On approval, the Registry MUST obtain a root Principal Token signed
        using the Principal Token signing profile above, with <tt>iss</tt>
        equal to the approving principal's DID and <tt>sub</tt> equal to the
        stored GrantRequest <tt>agent_aid</tt>. The Registry MAY construct
        the unsigned payload and present it to a principal-controlled
        Principal Wallet
        or signing component, but the final compact JWT MUST be signed by an
        Ed25519 verification method controlled by <tt>principal.id</tt>. The
        Registry MUST store the resulting GrantResponse without altering or
        re-signing the Principal Token.
      </li>
      <li>
        The deployer receives the GrantResponse and submits the
        Registration Envelope to POST /v1/agents with grant_tier: "G1".
      </li>
    </ol>

    <t>
      <strong>GET /v1/grants/{grant_id} authorisation:</strong> Only the
      deployer whose deployer_did appears in the original GrantRequest
      MUST be permitted to retrieve the GrantResponse.
    </t>
    <t>
      If <tt>grant_id</tt> does not identify a stored G1 grant, or if the
      referenced grant is expired and no GrantResponse is retrievable, the
      Registry MUST reject the request with <tt>grant_not_found</tt>.
    </t>
    <t>
      If <tt>grant_id</tt> identifies a stored, retrievable G1 grant but the
      authenticated requester does not match the <tt>deployer_did</tt> in the
      original GrantRequest, the Registry MUST reject the request with
      <tt>grant_deployer_mismatch</tt>.
    </t>
    <t>
      If <tt>grant_id</tt> identifies a stored G1 grant whose principal
      outcome is <tt>"rejected"</tt>, the Registry MUST reject the retrieval
      request with <tt>grant_rejected_by_principal</tt>. If the stored
      GrantResponse <tt>nonce</tt> does not match the original GrantRequest
      <tt>nonce</tt>, the Registry MUST reject the retrieval request with
      <tt>grant_nonce_mismatch</tt> and MUST NOT return the stored
      GrantResponse.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="g2-grant" numbered="true">
  <name>G2: Direct Deployer Grant Flow</name>
    <t>
      The G2 (Direct Deployer) grant profile is the standard flow for
      applications that integrate directly with Principal Wallets.
      The deployer signs the GrantRequest directly and transmits it
      to the Principal Wallet via a front-channel binding (Web Redirect or QR
      Code).
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Actors:</strong> Agent Deployer, Principal Wallet, Principal.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Step-by-step definition:</strong>
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>The deployer generates the agent's Ed25519 keypair, derives the
      agent AID, and constructs a GrantRequest that includes
      <tt>agent_aid</tt> and <tt>deployer_did</tt>.</li>
      <li>The deployer signs the GrantRequest as a compact JWS using the Ed25519 key identified by a <tt>kid</tt> under <tt>deployer_did</tt>.</li>
      <li>The deployer transmits the request to the Principal Wallet via a front-channel binding.</li>
      <li>The Principal Wallet resolves <tt>deployer_did</tt>, verifies the signed GrantRequest envelope, and presents the consent UI to the principal only after successful verification.</li>
      <li>On approval, the Principal Wallet signs the Principal Token using the Principal Token signing profile above and returns a GrantResponse to the deployer's callback_uri.</li>
      <li>The deployer submits the Registration Envelope to the Registry with grant_tier: "G2".</li>
    </ol>
  </section>

  <section anchor="g3-grant" numbered="true">
  <name>G3: Full Ceremony Grant Flow (OAuth 2.1)</name>
    <t>
      The G3 (Full Ceremony) grant profile is required for high-assurance
      Tier 3 operations and environments requiring identity proofing.
      It uses an OAuth 2.1 Authorization Server (AS) typically operated
      by the Registry.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Actors:</strong> Agent Deployer, AIP Registry (as OAuth AS),
      Principal Wallet, Principal.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>OAuth binding of the GrantRequest:</strong> Before initiating
      the OAuth authorization request, the deployer MUST construct and sign a
      GrantRequest using the signed GrantRequest envelope defined in Section
      12.2. The G3 OAuth authorization request MUST carry that compact JWS in
      an <tt>aip_grant_request</tt> form parameter. The authorization request
      MUST also include <tt>response_type=code</tt>, <tt>client_id</tt>,
      <tt>redirect_uri</tt>, <tt>scope</tt>, <tt>state</tt>,
      <tt>code_challenge</tt>, <tt>code_challenge_method=S256</tt>,
      <tt>acr_values</tt>, and <tt>aip_version=0.3</tt>.
    </t>

    <artwork type="example"><![CDATA[
POST /v1/oauth/authorize
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

response_type=code
&client_id=did:web:assistant.example.com
&redirect_uri=https://assistant.example.com/aip/grant-callback
&scope=email.read%20calendar.read
&state=sess_abc123_csrf_xyz789
&code_challenge=<S256-code-challenge>
&code_challenge_method=S256
&acr_values=<requested-acr>
&aip_version=0.3
&aip_grant_request=<compact-JWS-signed-GrantRequest>
]]></artwork>

    <t>
      The Registry Authorization Server MUST verify the signed
      GrantRequest envelope before redirecting the principal to a Principal
      Wallet or displaying any consent UI. Verification MUST include the signed
      GrantRequest checks in Section 12.2 and the following G3 binding
      checks:
    </t>
    <ol type="%d">
      <li>The <tt>aip_grant_request</tt> parameter is present and contains a
      compact JWS whose payload is a GrantRequest object.</li>
      <li>The OAuth <tt>client_id</tt> either equals the GrantRequest
      <tt>deployer_did</tt> or identifies a pre-registered OAuth client whose
      Registry metadata maps to that same <tt>deployer_did</tt>.</li>
      <li>The OAuth <tt>redirect_uri</tt> exactly matches the GrantRequest
      <tt>callback_uri</tt>.</li>
      <li>The OAuth <tt>state</tt> exactly matches the GrantRequest
      <tt>state</tt>.</li>
      <li>The GrantRequest <tt>request_expires_at</tt> has not passed,
      allowing at most 30 seconds of clock skew.</li>
      <li>The OAuth <tt>scope</tt> parameter does not request authority
      outside the GrantRequest <tt>requested_capabilities</tt>. If the
      Authorization Server cannot map a requested scope string to the
      GrantRequest capabilities under the synced AIP Scope Catalog, it MUST
      treat the authorization request as invalid.</li>
    </ol>
    <t>
      If any binding check fails, the Authorization Server MUST reject the
      authorization request with <tt>grant_request_invalid</tt> and MUST NOT
      issue an authorization code. After successful verification, the
      Authorization Server MUST store an immutable authorization-code binding
      that includes the JCS hash of the GrantRequest payload, the compact JWS
      signature value, <tt>grant_request_id</tt>, <tt>agent_aid</tt>,
      <tt>deployer_did</tt>, <tt>nonce</tt>, <tt>state</tt>,
      <tt>callback_uri</tt>, <tt>requested_capabilities</tt>, and
      <tt>delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt>. The token endpoint MUST use this
      stored binding when redeeming the authorization code and MUST reject
      any code that lacks such a binding with <tt>grant_request_invalid</tt>.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>G3 token endpoint response mapping:</strong> A successful
      <tt>POST /v1/oauth/token</tt> response for a G3 grant ceremony is an
      OAuth token response that transports, but does not replace, an AIP
      GrantResponse. The response body MUST be a JSON object with the following
      fields:
    </t>

    <ul>
      <li><tt>token_type</tt>: REQUIRED. MUST be <tt>"AIP+JWT"</tt>.</li>
      <li><tt>access_token</tt>: REQUIRED. The compact Principal Token JWT.
      This value is an OAuth transport alias only.</li>
      <li><tt>expires_in</tt>: REQUIRED. Integer seconds until the Principal
      Token expires; MUST equal
      <tt>grant_response.approved_delegation_valid_for_seconds</tt>.</li>
      <li><tt>state</tt>: REQUIRED. MUST equal the OAuth
      <tt>state</tt> value stored in the authorization-code binding.</li>
      <li><tt>grant_response</tt>: REQUIRED. A JSON object conforming to the
      GrantResponse schema in Section 12.4 with <tt>status</tt> equal to
      <tt>"approved"</tt> or <tt>"partial"</tt>.</li>
    </ul>

    <t>
      The <tt>access_token</tt> value MUST be byte-for-byte identical to
      <tt>grant_response.principal_token</tt>. The deployer MUST validate the
      nested <tt>grant_response</tt> using the GrantResponse validation rules in
      Section 12.4 and MUST use <tt>grant_response.principal_token</tt> when
      constructing the Registration Envelope. The <tt>access_token</tt> field
      exists only for OAuth client interoperability and MUST NOT be interpreted
      as replacing the <tt>principal_token</tt> field. The Principal Token
      payload MUST include the <tt>acr</tt> and <tt>amr</tt> claims from the
      completed G3 ceremony. If the principal rejects the grant or the ceremony
      fails before approval, the Authorization Server MUST return an OAuth error
      response and MUST NOT return a successful token response.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Step-by-step definition:</strong>
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>The deployer constructs and signs a GrantRequest, then initiates an
      OAuth 2.1 Authorization Code Flow with PKCE at the Registry's
      authorization endpoint using the G3 OAuth binding above.</li>
      <li>The Registry redirects the principal to their configured Principal Wallet for authentication and consent.</li>
      <li>The Principal Wallet performs high-assurance authentication (e.g., FIDO2/WebAuthn) and obtains consent.</li>
      <li>The Principal Wallet returns an authorization code or equivalent signed
      ceremony result to the Registry.</li>
      <li>The Registry MUST obtain a root Principal Token signed using the
      Principal Token signing profile above by a principal-controlled Ed25519
      verification method. The Registry MAY prepare the token payload and
      include the high-assurance <tt>acr</tt> and <tt>amr</tt> values from the
      OAuth ceremony, but it MUST NOT sign the root Principal Token with the
      Registry's authorization-server key and MUST NOT change <tt>iss</tt>
      away from <tt>principal.id</tt>. The token <tt>sub</tt> MUST equal the
      <tt>agent_aid</tt> value from the stored authorization-code binding,
      and the token MUST include <tt>acr</tt> and <tt>amr</tt> claims from
      the completed ceremony.</li>
      <li>The token endpoint returns the G3 token endpoint response defined
      above. Its <tt>grant_response</tt> member is the AIP GrantResponse used
      by the deployer for Registration Envelope construction.</li>
      <li>The deployer submits the Registration Envelope to the Registry with grant_tier: "G3".</li>
    </ol>
  </section>
</section>
