<section anchor="rate-limiting">
  <name>Rate Limiting and Abuse Prevention</name>
  <t>
    Rate limiting protects the Registry from denial-of-service attacks,
    registration floods, and validation-driven key lookup storms. A
    public Registry that permits unrestricted write operations or
    validation-driven lookups is exploitable in ways that undermine the
    security guarantees of the entire ecosystem.
  </t>

  <section anchor="rate-limit-response-format">
    <name>Rate Limit Response Format</name>
    <t>
      When rate limiting is applied, the Registry MUST return HTTP 429 with
      the following headers:
    </t>
    <table>
      <thead>
        <tr><th>Header</th><th>Required</th><th>Description</th></tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr><td><tt>Retry-After</tt></td><td>MUST</td><td>Seconds until the client may retry, or a HTTP-date per [RFC9110]</td></tr>
        <tr><td><tt>X-RateLimit-Limit</tt></td><td>SHOULD</td><td>The request limit for this window</td></tr>
        <tr><td><tt>X-RateLimit-Remaining</tt></td><td>SHOULD</td><td>Remaining requests in this window</td></tr>
        <tr><td><tt>X-RateLimit-Reset</tt></td><td>SHOULD</td><td>Unix timestamp when the window resets</td></tr>
        <tr><td><tt>X-RateLimit-Policy</tt></td><td>MAY</td><td>Human-readable description of the applicable policy</td></tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <t>
      The response body MUST conform to the error response format (Section 18.1)
      with <tt>error: "rate_limit_exceeded"</tt> and a human-readable
      <tt>error_description</tt> identifying the rate-limited operation and the
      applicable window.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="rate-limit-categories">
    <name>Per-Endpoint Rate Limit Categories</name>
    <t>
      The Registry MUST implement separate rate limit buckets for each of
      the following operation categories. The numeric limits below are
      RECOMMENDED default ceilings for unauthenticated or baseline clients.
      Registry operators MAY enforce lower ceilings when observed traffic
      patterns or threat models require stricter throttling, and MAY grant
      higher ceilings to authenticated or verified clients where this section
      allows higher limits.
      Rate-limit conformance is based on implementing the separate buckets,
      enforcing a documented effective limit for each bucket, and returning the
      response format in Section 19.1. The exact numeric thresholds are
      operational policy unless a requirement below uses MUST.
    </t>

    <section anchor="rate-limit-category-r1">
      <name>Category R1 - Registration writes</name>
      <t>
        (<tt>POST /v1/agents</tt>):
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Per-principal-DID: RECOMMENDED limit of 20 agent registrations per
          hour. This prevents a single compromised principal key from flooding
          the Registry with rogue agent registrations.
        </li>
        <li>
          Per-source-IP: RECOMMENDED limit of 50 registrations per hour
          across all principals. This prevents registration floods from a
          single network origin, regardless of the principal DID presented.
        </li>
        <li>
          Global: Registries SHOULD implement a global registration rate limit
          appropriate to their infrastructure capacity.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rate-limit-category-r2">
      <name>Category R2 - Key rotation writes</name>
      <t>
        (<tt>PUT /v1/agents/{aid}</tt>):
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Per-AID: RECOMMENDED limit of 10 key rotations per 24-hour window.
          Legitimate key rotation is infrequent; high frequency suggests
          automated abuse or a compromised orchestrator.
        </li>
        <li>
          Emergency Key Rotation
          (<xref target="agent-emergency-key-rotation-registry"/>): Registries
          MUST apply a stricter per-AID limit to requests processed as
          Emergency Key Rotation attempts, including rejected attempts.
          RECOMMENDED limit: 3 attempts per 24-hour window per AID. A
          legitimate agent performs Emergency Key Rotation at most once per
          fallback key; repeated attempts indicate probing of the fallback
          recovery path and SHOULD additionally trigger operator
          alerting.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rate-limit-category-r3">
      <name>Category R3 - Revocation writes</name>
      <t>
        (<tt>POST /v1/revocations</tt>):
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Per-issuer-DID: RECOMMENDED limit of 100 revocations per hour.
          Higher limits are legitimate for enterprise orchestrators managing
          large ephemeral agent fleets. Registries MAY issue higher limits to
          verified principals.
        </li>
        <li>
          Registries MUST apply special throttling to
          <tt>propagate_to_children: true</tt> revocations that would cascade
          to more than 100 descendants,
          as these trigger recursive Registry writes. A revocation that would
          cascade to more than 100 descendants SHOULD be queued and processed
          asynchronously, with the Registry returning HTTP 202 (Accepted) and
          a status URI rather than blocking on the full cascade.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rate-limit-category-r4">
      <name>Category R4 - Validation-driven key reads</name>
      <t>
        (<tt>GET /v1/agents/{aid}/public-key/{key-id}</tt>,
        <tt>GET /v1/agents/{aid}/revocation</tt>):
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Per-requesting-IP: RECOMMENDED limit of 1,000 requests per minute
          across all AIDs. Validation-driven reads are triggered by token
          verification; legitimate Relying Parties have bounded lookup rates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Per-AID: RECOMMENDED limit of 200 reads per minute. A single AID
          being looked up 200 times per minute from varied IPs is likely the
          subject of a coordinated replay attack; rate limiting per AID
          allows the Registry to throttle targeted abuse.
        </li>
        <li>
          Registries SHOULD offer API key authentication for Relying Parties
          whose legitimate validation rates exceed these limits (e.g.,
          high-traffic APIs that verify thousands of agent tokens per minute).
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rate-limit-category-r5">
      <name>Category R5 - CRL reads</name>
      <t>
        (<tt>GET /v1/crl</tt> direct-origin reads and the published
        <tt>endpoints.crl</tt> retrieval URI):
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          The published CRL retrieval URI MUST be served from a CDN or
          distributed infrastructure (<xref target="crl"/>). Direct-origin CRL reads
          to <tt>/v1/crl</tt> SHOULD be rate limited per IP to 100 requests
          per minute to protect against CDN bypass attacks. CDN-served
          responses have no normative rate limit constraint.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rate-limit-category-r6">
      <name>Category R6 - Endorsement writes</name>
      <t>
        (<tt>POST /v1/endorsements</tt>):
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Per-from-AID: RECOMMENDED limit of 500 endorsements per hour. This
          prevents an AID from artificially inflating another AID's
          <tt>endorsement_count</tt> through automated submission.
        </li>
        <li>
          Self-endorsement (<tt>from_aid</tt> == <tt>to_aid</tt>) MUST be rejected at the
          application layer before rate limits are checked.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rate-limit-category-r7">
      <name>Category R7 - Approval Envelope writes and step claims</name>
      <t>
        (<tt>POST /v1/approvals</tt>, <tt>POST /v1/approvals/{id}/steps/{n}/claim</tt>):
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Per-principal-DID: RECOMMENDED limit of 100 Approval Envelopes per
          hour. Approval Envelopes represent human-authorised workflows;
          high frequency is anomalous.
        </li>
        <li>
          Per-actor-AID per envelope: step claims are naturally rate-limited
          by the sequential structure of the workflow. No additional rate
          limit is required for step claims within a single envelope.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="registration-abuse-prevention">
    <name>Registration Abuse Prevention</name>
    <t>
      Beyond rate limiting, the Registry MUST implement the following
      structural checks to prevent registration abuse:
    </t>

    <section anchor="aid-uniqueness-enforcement">
      <name>AID uniqueness enforcement</name>
      <t>
        The Registry MUST check AID uniqueness under a distributed lock or
        equivalent atomic mechanism. Two simultaneous registration requests
        for the same AID MUST result in exactly one succeeding and one
        receiving an appropriate error (Section 6.2 Check 4).
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="principal-delegation-chain-verification">
      <name>Principal delegation chain verification at registration</name>
      <t>
        The Registry MUST verify that the <tt>principal_token</tt> in the Registration
        Envelope was issued by a DID that is resolvable and has not been
        subjected to a <tt>full_revoke</tt> or <tt>principal_revoke</tt> RevocationObject
        in the Registry. A revoked principal MUST NOT be permitted to
        register new agents.
      </t>
      <t>
        For the purposes of this check, a <strong>revoked principal</strong> is
        defined as a principal DID (<tt>principal_token.principal.id</tt>)
        against which a <tt>principal_revoke</tt> Revocation Object has been
        submitted to this Registry. The Registry MUST maintain an index of
        principal DIDs associated with <tt>principal_revoke</tt> revocations and
        MUST reject new Registration Envelopes where
        <tt>principal_token.principal.id</tt> matches a DID in this index. A
        <tt>principal_revoke</tt> whose <tt>target_id</tt> is a Principal DID is
        principal-wide. A <tt>principal_revoke</tt> whose <tt>target_id</tt> is a
        specific agent AID is scoped to that AID's authorisation and does not by
        itself block registration of unrelated AIDs for the same principal.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="registration-flood-from-shared-principals">
      <name>Registration flood from shared principals</name>
      <t>
        Operational guidance (non-normative): a high number of registrations
        under a single principal DID can be an abuse signal. A Registry can
        apply local policy, such as deployer review or out-of-band business
        verification, when registrations from one principal exceed an
        implementation-defined threshold. A value such as 1,000 agents can be
        used as an example review trigger, but this specification does not
        define a protocol-visible proof of legitimate use, an interoperable
        review mechanism, or a conformance threshold for shared-principal
        registration volume.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="public-registry-challenge">
      <name>Public Registry challenge for unauthenticated deployers</name>
      <t>
        Registries that permit registration without deployer authentication
        (open Registries) SHOULD implement a lightweight proof-of-work or
        CAPTCHA mechanism for registrations where the deployer DID is
        self-asserted, unauthenticated to the Registry, or otherwise not
        trusted by local Registry policy.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="validation-driven-lookup-limits">
    <name>Validation-Driven Lookup Limits</name>
    <t>
      Key lookup amplification occurs when an adversary presents many tokens
      with distinct <tt>kid</tt> values, forcing the Registry to perform a lookup
      for each. Mitigations:
    </t>

    <section anchor="key-version-caching">
      <name>Key version caching</name>
      <t>
        Relying Parties MUST cache resolved public keys for a given <tt>kid</tt>
        for up to 300 seconds. Repeated validation of tokens
        with the same <tt>kid</tt> SHOULD NOT trigger repeated Registry lookups
        within the cache window.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="historical-key-depth-limit">
      <name>Historical key depth limit</name>
      <t>
        Registries MAY reject requests for key versions older than the
        historical key retention window defined in Section 19.7. This prevents
        adversaries from constructing tokens with ancient, never-rotated keys
        to force deep history lookups without invalidating any conforming
        unexpired token.
      </t>
      <t>
        Relying Parties perform the Step 2a expiration preflight before
        historical key lookup. Therefore an expired token MUST be rejected with
        <tt>token_expired</tt> before a missing historical key can produce
        <tt>unknown_aid</tt>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="kid-validation-at-relying-party">
      <name><tt>kid</tt> validation at the Relying Party</name>
      <t>
        Relying Parties MUST validate that the <tt>kid</tt> in the token header
        matches the pattern:
        <tt>did:aip:&lt;lowercase-namespace&gt;:&lt;32-lowercase-hex&gt;#key-&lt;positive-integer&gt;</tt>
        before performing any Registry lookup (Validation Step 3).
        Malformed <tt>kid</tt> values MUST be rejected with <tt>invalid_token</tt>
        without making a Registry call.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="approval-envelope-rate-limits">
    <name>Approval Envelope Rate Limits</name>
    <t>
      Approval Envelope operations require specific abuse prevention because
      they involve asynchronous principal interactions and potential cascade
      effects.
    </t>

    <section anchor="envelope-submission-rate">
      <name>Envelope submission rate</name>
      <t>
        Per Section 19.2, Category R7.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="pending-envelope-limit">
      <name>Pending envelope limit</name>
      <t>
        A Registry SHOULD enforce a maximum of 1,000 <tt>pending_approval</tt>
        envelopes per principal DID at any time. Envelopes that expire
        transition to <tt>expired</tt> and free this quota.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="step-claim-timeout">
      <name>Step claim timeout</name>
      <t>
        Step claims that are not completed or failed within the Registry's
        published <tt>step_claim_timeout_seconds</tt> value MUST be
        automatically failed by the Registry. The timeout interval starts at
        the step's <tt>claimed_at</tt> timestamp. The
        <tt>step_claim_timeout_seconds</tt> value MUST be an integer from 1
        to 600 seconds inclusive and MUST be published in
        <tt>/v1/registry-metadata</tt>.
      </t>
      <t>
        This prevents a claimed step from blocking the workflow indefinitely
        due to a crashed or unresponsive agent. Timeout-induced failure MUST
        trigger the same envelope failure and compensation evaluation as an
        explicit step failure reported by the actor.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="compensation-cascade-depth">
      <name>Compensation cascade depth</name>
      <t>
        Compensation step execution is not rate-limited separately - it is
        a recovery mechanism whose scope is bounded by the number of forward
        steps (maximum 20). No additional rate limit is required for
        compensation.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="graduated-backoff-requirements">
    <name>Graduated Backoff Requirements</name>
    <t>
      Clients that receive HTTP 429 responses MUST implement exponential
      backoff with jitter. The minimum retry interval is the value in the
      <tt>Retry-After</tt> header. Clients MUST NOT retry before <tt>Retry-After</tt>
      expires.
    </t>
    <t>
      Implementations SHOULD use the following backoff formula:
    </t>
    <artwork type="pseudocode"><![CDATA[
BACKOFF_BASE = 1         ; fixed exponential base, in seconds
MAX_DELAY    = 3600      ; hard ceiling, in seconds

computed_delay = min(BACKOFF_BASE * 2^attempt, MAX_DELAY)
jitter         = random(0, BACKOFF_BASE)
retry_delay    = max(computed_delay + jitter, Retry-After)
    ]]></artwork>
    <t>
      The <tt>Retry-After</tt> value from the 429 response acts as a mandatory
      minimum: clients MUST NOT retry before <tt>Retry-After</tt> seconds have
      elapsed, even if <tt>computed_delay + jitter</tt> is smaller. When no
      <tt>Retry-After</tt> header is present, clients MUST treat it as 0 and
      rely solely on the exponential formula.
    </t>
    <t>
      Clients that continue to receive HTTP 429 after 5 exponential backoff
      attempts MUST cease retrying for a minimum of 1 hour and SHOULD alert
      an operator. Persistent rate limiting at this scale indicates either
      a misconfigured client or a sustained attack pattern.
    </t>
    <t>
      Registries MUST track clients that consistently exceed rate limits and
      MAY temporarily block their source IPs or API keys after sustained
      abuse. Blocking decisions are implementation-specific and are not
      normatively constrained by this specification.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="historical-key-retention-requirements">
    <name>Historical Key Retention Requirements</name>
    <t>
      A Registry that accepts key rotation for an AID MUST retain each retired
      public verification key for historical validation until at least:
    </t>
    <artwork type="pseudocode"><![CDATA[
retention_not_before =
  retired_key.valid_until
  + max_credential_token_ttl_for_registry
  + accepted_clock_skew
    ]]></artwork>
    <t>
      <tt>max_credential_token_ttl_for_registry</tt> is the largest effective
      Credential Token TTL that the Registry could have accepted for any active
      scope at the time the key was retired, after applying the Tier ceilings in
      <xref target="token-issuance"/> and the synced AIP Scope Catalog. The
      <tt>accepted_clock_skew</tt> value MUST be at least 30 seconds.
      Registries MAY retain retired keys longer than this minimum. The
      RECOMMENDED operational retention window is 90 days after
      <tt>valid_until</tt>, but that window MUST be extended when the formula
      above yields a later time.
    </t>
    <t>
      Historical key retention is a validation-availability rule, not an
      authority extension. Agents MUST stop issuing Credential Tokens with a
      retired private key immediately after a successful rotation, and Relying
      Parties MUST still reject tokens whose <tt>exp</tt>, delegation chain, or
      revocation state fails validation.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
