<section anchor="security" numbered="true">
  <name>Security Considerations</name>
  <t>
    This section describes the security considerations for
    AIP implementations, including the threat model, cryptographic
    requirements, and recommended mitigations.
  </t>

  <section anchor="threat-model" numbered="true">
  <name>Threat Model</name>
    <t>
      AIP identifies the following threat categories:
    </t>

    <dl newline="true">
      <dt>TS-1: Token Replay</dt>
      <dd>An adversary reuses a captured Credential Token. Mitigation: JTI replay cache.</dd>

      <dt>TS-2: Key Compromise</dt>
      <dd>An adversary steals an agent's private key. Mitigation: Key rotation, HSM storage.</dd>

      <dt>TS-3: Delegation Escalation</dt>
      <dd>A child agent exceeds granted scope. Mitigation: Rule D-1 (Scope Inheritance), Step 9c validation.</dd>

      <dt>TS-4: Registry Impersonation</dt>
      <dd>A malicious Registry serves fake revocation status. Mitigation: Well-known configuration, key pinning.</dd>

      <dt>TS-5: Principal Impersonation</dt>
      <dd>An adversary forges a Principal Token. Mitigation: DID resolution verification.</dd>

      <dt>TS-6: Revocation Delay</dt>
      <dd>The gap between revocation issue and propagation. Mitigation: Real-time RPNP for Tier 2.</dd>

      <dt>TS-7: Token Theft</dt>
      <dd>An adversary intercepts a token in transit. Mitigation: TLS 1.2+, DPoP.</dd>

      <dt>TS-8: Child Agent Self-Replication</dt>
      <dd>An agent with spawn_agents.create creates children during TTL window. Mitigation: Tier 2 with propagate_to_children.</dd>

      <dt>TS-9: Action Hash Manipulation</dt>
      <dd>An agent executes different action than approved. Mitigation: Action hash verification at claim time.</dd>

      <dt>TS-10: Step Execution Token Misuse</dt>
      <dd>An adversary forges, replays, or re-targets a Step Execution Token
        to execute an Approval Envelope step outside the authorized actor,
        audience, or step context. Mitigation: SET validation profile,
        Registry Trust Record step-execution keys, Step 10a verification,
        DPoP binding, and per-step status checks.</dd>

      <dt>TS-11: Approval Lifecycle Race</dt>
      <dd>Concurrent approval, rejection, expiry, cancellation, or claim
        operations produce inconsistent Approval Envelope state. Mitigation:
        atomic lifecycle transitions, compare-and-set or equivalent locking,
        terminal-state rules, and <tt>approval_state_conflict</tt>.</dd>

      <dt>TS-12: Orchestrator Cascade</dt>
      <dd>A compromised or over-privileged orchestrator uses one approval or
        delegation to trigger a larger cascade of dependent actions than the
        principal intended. Mitigation: pre-declared Approval Envelope steps,
        per-step actor and action-hash verification, step count limits,
        dedicated destructive-scope approval, and SAGA compensation rules.</dd>

      <dt>TS-13: Overlay Injection</dt>
      <dd>An adversary injects or replays a Capability Overlay to expand or
        mis-scope an agent's effective capabilities. Mitigation: Overlay
        signatures, issuer validation, monotonic overlay versions, CO-1
        attenuation-only validation, engagement scoping, and catalog
        constraint validation.</dd>

      <dt>TS-14: Engagement Tampering</dt>
      <dd>An adversary modifies Engagement Object participants, lifecycle
        state, approval gates, or change-log entries to alter authorization
        context. Mitigation: required countersignatures, append-only signed
        change logs, strict sequence validation, participant authorization
        checks, and termination cascade rules.</dd>

      <dt>TS-15: Model Substitution</dt>
      <dd>An agent deployer registers with a trusted model identifier but
        executes a different model binary or version manifest. Mitigation:
        <tt>model.attestation_hash</tt> SHOULD be present for Tier 2
        deployments and MUST be present for Tier 3 deployments. The Registry
        SHOULD accept a Tier 2 registration without
        <tt>model.attestation_hash</tt> only when it persists and returns the
        structured <tt>model_attestation_missing_tier2</tt> registration
        warning defined in Section 6.2. The Registry MUST reject a Tier 3
        registration when <tt>model.attestation_hash</tt> is absent.</dd>
    </dl>
  </section>

  <section anchor="crypto-requirements" numbered="true">
  <name>Cryptographic Requirements</name>
                <table>
          <name>Mandatory-to-Implement Cryptography</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Operation</th>
              <th align="left">Algorithm</th>
              <th align="left">Specification</th>
              <th align="center">Status</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>Signing / Verification</td>
              <td>Ed25519 (EdDSA)</td>
              <td><xref target="RFC8037"/></td>
              <td>MUST</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Hashing</td>
              <td>SHA-256</td>
              <td><xref target="FIPS-180-4"/></td>
              <td>MUST</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Key representation</td>
              <td>JWK</td>
              <td><xref target="RFC7517"/></td>
              <td>MUST</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

    <t>
      This specification does not define an AIP key-exchange or encryption
      handshake. X25519 and other key-agreement mechanisms are reserved for a
      future extension and are not mandatory-to-implement in Draft-02.
      Implementations MUST NOT treat support for any key-agreement algorithm
      as a condition for conformance to this specification.
    </t>

    <t>
      This specification reserves ES256 (ECDSA P-256) and RS256 (RSA-PKCS1),
      as defined by <xref target="RFC7518"/>, for possible future extensions
      but does not define registration, resolution, rotation, AID derivation,
      or DPoP binding rules for those suites in protocol version
      <tt>0.3</tt>. Credential Tokens, Principal Tokens, Step Execution
      Tokens, DPoP proofs, Agent Identity keys, and Registry public-key
      responses conforming to this specification MUST use EdDSA over Ed25519.
      Implementations MUST reject <tt>ES256</tt>, <tt>RS256</tt>, and other
      algorithm values for those artifacts.
    </t>

    <t>
      Prohibited: none, HS256/384/512, RS512, MD5, SHA-1.
      The alg header MUST be explicitly specified. A DID verification
      method used to sign or verify a Credential Token, Principal Token, Step
      Execution Token, or DPoP proof MUST be an Ed25519 signing verification
      method. X25519 keys are key-agreement keys and MUST NOT be used for
      signing.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="dpop" numbered="true">
  <name>Proof-of-Possession (DPoP)</name>
    <t>
      DPoP is REQUIRED for every Tier 2 or Tier 3 operation. It is also
      REQUIRED when any requested Tier 1 scope has
      <tt>requires_dpop: true</tt> in the synced AIP Scope Catalog, or when
      the target endpoint requires DPoP independently of scope metadata. DPoP proofs MUST use
      EdDSA.
    </t>
    <table>
      <name>DPoP Applicability</name>
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th align="left">Operation or request class</th>
          <th align="left">DPoP requirement</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <tr><td>Tier 1 operation with no DPoP-required scope and no endpoint policy</td><td>Not required by AIP.</td></tr>
        <tr><td>Tier 1 operation containing any scope whose synced Catalog entry has <tt>requires_dpop: true</tt></td><td>Required.</td></tr>
        <tr><td>Tier 1 Registry endpoint that independently requires DPoP, including key rotation, heartbeat submission, and RPNP subscription authentication</td><td>Required.</td></tr>
        <tr><td>Tier 2 operation</td><td>Required for every request.</td></tr>
        <tr><td>Tier 3 operation</td><td>Required for every request, in addition to mTLS.</td></tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
    <t>
      Endpoint-level DPoP requirements are independent of the operation's
      security Tier. For example, <tt>PUT /v1/agents/{aid}</tt> key rotation
      and <tt>POST /v1/agents/{aid}/heartbeat</tt> require DPoP even when the
      affected agent was originally registered only for Tier 1 scopes.
    </t>
    <t>
      For standard AIP scopes, the Draft-02 catalog marks all destructive
      scopes and selected high-risk external-effect scopes as DPoP-required.
      This includes deletion scopes, filesystem mutation and execution scopes,
      transactions, communication scopes, spawn-agent scopes, and the
      non-destructive but high-risk <tt>email.send</tt>,
      <tt>web.download</tt>, and <tt>web.forms_submit</tt> scopes.
      The <tt>web.forms_submit</tt> scope is Tier 2 in the Draft-02 catalog
      because form submissions can create external account, data, or financial
      effects.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>DPoP Proof Header:</strong>
    </t>

    <artwork type="example"><![CDATA[
{
  "typ": "dpop+jwt",
  "alg": "EdDSA",
  "jwk": {
    "kty": "OKP",
    "crv": "Ed25519",
    "x": "<base64url public key>",
    "kid": "<DID URL>"
  }
}
]]></artwork>

    <t>
      <strong>DPoP Proof Payload:</strong>
    </t>

    <artwork type="example"><![CDATA[
{
  "jti": "<UUID v4>",
  "htm": "<HTTP method, uppercase>",
  "htu": "<scheme + host + path, no query or fragment>",
  "iat": "<Unix timestamp>",
  "ath": "<BASE64URL(SHA-256(token))>"
}
]]></artwork>

    <t>
      Relying Party validation: Verify alg is EdDSA, verify htm/htu/iat,
      check jti replay, verify ath, verify signature, and verify the DPoP
      public key binding for the presented token type. For an agent-issued
      Credential Token, <tt>jwk.kid</tt> MUST match the Credential Token
      protected header <tt>kid</tt>. For a Step Execution Token,
      <tt>jwk.kid</tt> MUST identify Ed25519 public key material controlled
      by the SET <tt>sub</tt> actor AID; it MUST NOT be the Registry
      step-execution key that signed the SET.
    </t>
    <t>
      The <tt>htu</tt> claim is the DPoP target URI binding. It MUST match
      the absolute target URI of the current request, excluding query and
      fragment components and using the normalization rules in
      <xref target="RFC9449"/>. A proof captured for one Relying Party,
      Registry, host, path, or method is not transferable to another target:
      validation MUST fail on <tt>htu</tt> or <tt>htm</tt> before replay-cache
      state is considered.
    </t>
    <t>
      The <tt>ath</tt> claim binds the proof to the presented token. Its
      value MUST be the unpadded base64url encoding of the SHA-256 hash of
      the exact compact Credential Token or Step Execution Token value from
      the <tt>Authorization</tt> header, excluding the authorization scheme,
      surrounding whitespace, and DPoP proof. When DPoP is required, the
      authorization scheme is <tt>DPoP</tt>.
    </t>
    <t>
      DPoP proof <tt>jti</tt> replay state is verifier-local. A verifier MUST
      maintain a DPoP replay cache separate from the Credential Token replay
      cache and keyed by <tt>(kid, jti)</tt>. The cache window MUST be at
      least the accepted DPoP proof age window: 300 seconds before receipt
      plus 30 seconds of future clock skew, unless a server-provided DPoP
      nonce is required under <xref target="RFC9449"/>. When nonce validation
      is used, the replay cache MUST retain entries for at least the nonce
      lifetime. AIP does not require a global or cross-Registry DPoP replay
      cache because cross-target replay is rejected by <tt>htu</tt>,
      <tt>htm</tt>, and <tt>ath</tt> validation.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="key-management" numbered="true">
  <name>Key Management</name>
    <t>
      Private keys MUST NOT be stored in plaintext at rest,
      transmitted in protocol messages, or included in logs.
      Private keys SHOULD be stored in an HSM, secure enclave,
      OS-level keychain, or an equivalent protected key store where
      available.
    </t>

    <t>
      A private key satisfies the at-rest protection requirement when at least
      one of the following conditions is met:
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>The key is generated and used inside an HSM, secure enclave,
      operating-system keychain, cloud KMS, or comparable protected key store
      that prevents ordinary application processes from reading the raw private
      key material.</li>
      <li>The key is stored only as ciphertext produced by envelope encryption
      using AES-256-GCM, or an equivalent authenticated-encryption scheme with
      at least 128-bit security strength, unique nonce or IV use per
      encryption key, integrity authentication of the ciphertext, and
      associated data that binds the ciphertext to the AID, key identifier,
      key version, and intended key purpose.</li>
    </ol>

    <t>
      A protected key store or encryption design is equivalent for this
      specification only if it enforces access control for key use and key
      administration, separates key-encryption keys from encrypted private-key
      blobs, supports key-encryption-key rotation without exposing plaintext
      private keys, records administrative key export or deletion events, and
      does not depend on hard-coded wrapping keys or wrapping keys stored in
      the same plaintext database row, file, or object as the encrypted
      private key. Backup copies of private keys MUST satisfy the same
      controls as primary copies.
    </t>

    <t>
      The protected-key-store recommendation is a local implementation
      conformance requirement, not a wire-verifiable protocol condition.
      Registries and Relying Parties cannot determine from Credential Tokens
      or Registry API requests whether an implementation uses an HSM, secure
      enclave, keychain, or equivalent mechanism. They MUST NOT treat
      protected-key-store use as a Registry acceptance check or Credential
      Token validation precondition. Deployment profiles MAY require external
      audit, attestation, or certification of key-storage controls using the
      audit evidence profile below.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Deployment key-management audit evidence:</strong> A deployment
      profile that requires audit evidence for local key-management controls
      MUST define an audit interval and MUST collect, at minimum, the following
      evidence without recording private key material, seed material, or
      plaintext recovery secrets:
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>Key inventory records identifying each AID, key identifier,
      <tt>identity.version</tt>, key creation time, key activation time, key
      retirement time when applicable, and the protected storage boundary used
      for the key.</li>
      <li>Control evidence that private keys are not stored in plaintext at
      rest, transmitted in protocol messages, or included in logs. Acceptable
      evidence includes configuration attestations, HSM or secure-enclave
      policy exports, operating-system keychain policy exports, or signed
      operator attestations bound to a deployment profile.</li>
      <li>Rotation records for every key rotation, including the old key
      identifier, new key identifier, submitted Agent Identity version,
      <tt>previous_key_signature</tt> verification result, Registry acceptance
      time, and the time at which issuance with the retiring private key
      stopped.</li>
      <li>Compromise-response records for every
      <tt>key_compromised</tt> event, including the Revocation Object
      identifier, affected AID, time of revocation submission, and delegation
      re-establishment records if a replacement AID is registered.</li>
      <li>For sub-agent delegation where the parent generates the child key,
      provisioning and deletion records containing the parent AID, child AID,
      provisioning time, secure channel or key-wrapping mechanism identifier,
      deletion time for any parent-held child private-key copy, and the local
      process or operator identity that performed the deletion.</li>
    </ol>

    <t>
      Audit records for <tt>key_compromised</tt> events MUST NOT include
      verbatim Credential Token or Step Execution Token payloads. Token
      metadata (AID, <tt>jti</tt>, scope list, <tt>iat</tt>, <tt>exp</tt>) is
      sufficient for key-compromise timeline reconstruction and is the maximum
      permissible audit record content for token-related events.
    </t>

    <t>
      Audit evidence MAY be reviewed by deployment operators, external
      auditors, or certification programs, but it is not exchanged as part of
      Credential Token validation. A Registry or Relying Party MUST NOT reject
      an otherwise valid protocol message solely because this audit evidence is
      absent from the wire message. Unless a deployment claims the Deployment
      Key-Management Audit Profile in <xref target="optional-feature-profiles"/>,
      compliance with these local key-management controls is self-attested by
      the implementation's conformance claim.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Key rotation:</strong> Generate a new keypair, increment
      version, include <tt>previous_key_signature</tt> signed by the retiring
      key, and submit the new public key to the Registry. The Registry MUST
      retain the retiring public verification key according to the historical
      key retention rule in Section 19.7. The agent MUST stop issuing new
      tokens with the retiring private key after rotation succeeds.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Key compromise response:</strong> Immediately revoke with
      reason: key_compromised. If a fallback key is registered and is not
      itself suspected of compromise, perform Emergency Key Rotation
      (<xref target="agent-emergency-key-rotation-registry"/>) to retain the
      AID and its delegation history. If no fallback key is registered, or
      the fallback key may also be compromised, register a new AID with a
      new keypair and re-establish delegations.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="fallback-key-security" numbered="true">
    <name>Fallback Key and Emergency Rotation</name>
    <t>
      The fallback key (Section 5) is a recovery credential with the same
      authority as the active key: whoever holds the fallback private key can
      take permanent control of the AID through Emergency Key Rotation
      (<xref target="agent-emergency-key-rotation-registry"/>). Deployments
      that register a fallback key MUST protect the fallback private key at
      least as strongly as the active private key, and SHOULD store it in a
      separate protection boundary — offline or in a distinct HSM, secure
      enclave, or escrow system — so that a single compromise event cannot
      capture both keys. The fallback private key is needed exactly twice in
      normal operation: once to compute <tt>fallback_key_proof</tt> before
      registration, and once if Emergency Key Rotation is ever performed. It
      never needs to be online in between.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>Loss versus compromise:</strong> Emergency Key Rotation is the
      correct response to loss of the active private key, and to compromise
      of the active private key when the fallback key remains trustworthy.
      If the fallback private key is, or may be, compromised — including
      whenever active and fallback keys were stored in the same protection
      boundary during a compromise event — the operator MUST NOT rely on
      Emergency Key Rotation; the correct response is revocation with reason
      <tt>key_compromised</tt> followed by registration of a new AID. An
      attacker who obtains the fallback private key can silently take over
      the AID; the <tt>compromised</tt> key status, CRL entry, and operator
      alerting required by
      <xref target="agent-emergency-key-rotation-registry"/> exist so that
      such a takeover is observable rather than silent.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>Proof of possession:</strong> Registration Check 5c exists so
      that a fallback key cannot be registered without control of its private
      half. This prevents two failure modes: an operator registering a key
      it cannot use (an unrecoverable AID that appears recoverable) and an
      attacker squatting on a third party's public key as a fallback to
      block that party's future registrations. Verifiers other than the
      Registry MUST NOT treat the presence of a fallback key or proof as an
      endorsement of the agent.
    </t>
    <t>
      <strong>Single use and consumption:</strong> A fallback key
      authenticates at most one Emergency Key Rotation, and a consumed
      fallback key value is permanently unacceptable Registry-wide. This
      bounds the value of a stolen fallback key to a single observable
      takeover attempt and prevents replay of a recorded recovery across
      AIDs. An agent that performs Emergency Key Rotation SHOULD register a
      new fallback key in the same rotation request, because the protocol
      provides no later opportunity to add one. <tt>fallback_public_key_x</tt>
      is part of the public Agent Identity Object; the design assumes no
      secrecy for the fallback public key, and Registries MUST NOT treat
      knowledge of it as authenticating.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="token-security" numbered="true">
  <name>Token Security</name>
    <t>
      All tokens MUST be transmitted over TLS 1.2 or higher
      (TLS 1.3 RECOMMENDED). MUST NOT transmit over
      unencrypted HTTP.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>JTI replay cache:</strong> Keyed by (iss, jti);
      window at least max TTL for served scopes;
      shared cache for distributed deployments. The issuer AID is the replay
      domain: an agent MUST NOT reuse a <tt>jti</tt> across different
      delegation chains, principals, grants, scopes, or audiences.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Audience validation:</strong> MUST validate aud claim.
      Mismatch returns invalid_token.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="mtls-certificate-profile" numbered="true">
  <name>Tier 3 mTLS Certificate Profile</name>
    <t>
      Tier 3 operations require mutual TLS with an X.509 client certificate
      that binds the TLS client to the effective actor AID. The binding MUST
      use the certificate <tt>subjectAltName</tt> extension, not the subject
      DN or common name.
    </t>

    <ol>
      <li>The Relying Party MUST validate the client certificate path per
      <xref target="RFC5280"/> to a trust anchor explicitly configured for the
      target Registry, resource server, or deployment profile. The public Web
      PKI MUST NOT be treated as sufficient for AIP actor binding unless that
      CA set is explicitly configured as the deployment's Tier 3 client-certificate
      trust anchor set.</li>
      <li>The certificate MUST be within its validity interval, MUST permit
      digital signatures in <tt>keyUsage</tt> when <tt>keyUsage</tt> is
      present, and MUST contain the <tt>id-kp-clientAuth</tt> extended key
      usage when <tt>extendedKeyUsage</tt> is present.</li>
      <li>The certificate MUST contain exactly one URI
      <tt>subjectAltName</tt> value that matches the <tt>did:aip</tt> AID
      syntax. That URI SAN value is the certificate actor AID. The Relying
      Party MUST compare it byte-for-byte to the effective actor AID after
      ordinary URI SAN string extraction; it MUST NOT use subject DN, common
      name, email SAN, DNS SAN, or organization fields for actor binding.</li>
      <li>If the client certificate is absent, the Relying Party MUST reject
      with <tt>mtls_required</tt>. If path validation fails, required
      key-usage or EKU checks fail, the AIP URI SAN is absent, more than one
      AIP URI SAN is present, or the AIP URI SAN does not equal the effective
      actor AID, the Relying Party MUST reject with
      <tt>invalid_token</tt>.</li>
      <li>The Relying Party MUST perform certificate revocation checking using
      OCSP per <xref target="RFC6960"/> or a deployment-profile mechanism that
      provides at least equivalent freshness and issuer authorization. An
      equivalent deployment-profile mechanism MUST, at minimum, bind status to
      the certificate issuer or delegated status authority, provide signed or
      otherwise authenticated certificate status, define a maximum status
      freshness interval no weaker than the OCSP policy it replaces, fail
      closed on unavailable or indeterminate status, and be documented in the
      deployment's <tt>mtls_trust_anchors_uri</tt> material. A revoked client
      certificate MUST be rejected with
      <tt>agent_revoked</tt>. An unavailable, stale, or indeterminate
      certificate revocation status MUST be rejected with
      <tt>invalid_token</tt>.</li>
    </ol>

    <t>
      A Registry or deployment that accepts Tier 3 registrations or advertises
      Tier 3 operation support MUST document the client-certificate trust
      anchor set and revocation-checking mechanism. If this information is
      published through Registry Metadata, the fields are
      <tt>mtls_client_certificate_profile</tt> and
      <tt>mtls_trust_anchors_uri</tt>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="delegation-security" numbered="true">
  <name>Delegation Chain Security</name>
    <t>
      Default max_delegation_depth MUST NOT exceed 3.
      Hard cap is 10. Circular delegation MUST be detected
      and rejected.
    </t>

    <t>
      Ephemeral agents MUST have non-null <tt>task_id</tt>. The Registry
      MUST auto-revoke ephemeral agents when their
      <tt>lifecycle_expires_at</tt> deadline passes, as defined in
      Section 15. A Registry that leaves an ephemeral AID active after that
      deadline is non-conformant, even if Relying Parties would separately
      reject expired Principal Tokens or Capability Manifests during
      validation.
    </t>

    <t>
      Parent agents that generate child-agent private keys during
      sub-agent delegation MUST delete any retained copy after successful
      provisioning. This requirement is not wire-verifiable by Registries
      or Relying Parties; it is an implementation conformance requirement
      for the parent agent's key-management boundary. Deployment profiles that
      audit this requirement MUST use the sub-agent provisioning and deletion
      evidence defined in <xref target="key-management"/>.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="registry-security" numbered="true">
  <name>Registry Security</name>
    <t>
      All write operations MUST be authenticated.
      Revocation <tt>issued_by</tt>, <tt>kid</tt>, issuer authorization, and
      signature verification MUST follow the ordered Revocation Submission
      Validation algorithm in <xref target="revocation-submission-validation"/>.
    </t>

    <t>
      Registry read endpoint availability is an operational service-level
      objective, not a wire-protocol conformance condition. Deployment
      profiles MAY define measurable availability targets, measurement
      intervals, exclusions, evidence, and remedies. This specification does
      not define conformance failure solely by an uptime percentage. CRL MUST
      be served from CDN.
    </t>

    <t>
      Relying Parties MUST NOT trust the aip_registry
      claim in a Credential Token as sole indicator.
      For Tier 2, the authoritative Registry MUST be
      verified via the root principal's DID Document.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="revocation-security" numbered="true">
  <name>Revocation Security</name>
    <t>
      Every Revocation Object MUST be signed. Unsigned
      or invalidly signed objects MUST be rejected.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Dead Man's Switch (Optional):</strong> Registry
      MAY issue <tt>full_revoke</tt> for agents that fail to submit
      an authenticated heartbeat to
      <tt>POST /v1/agents/{aid}/heartbeat</tt> within a configured window
      (RECOMMENDED: 24 hours). The heartbeat authentication and liveness
      timestamp rules are defined in <xref target="agent-heartbeat-registry"/>.
    </t>

    <t>
      Registries that enable the Dead Man's Switch for an AID MUST measure
      the timeout from the Registry-recorded <tt>last_heartbeat_at</tt> value
      or, if no heartbeat has been accepted, from the AID registration time.
      When issuing an automatic revocation for heartbeat timeout, the Registry
      SHOULD use revocation reason <tt>heartbeat_timeout</tt>.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Timing attack mitigation:</strong> Short
      <tt>ttl_max_seconds</tt> values for sensitive scopes in the synced AIP
      Scope Catalog limit exploitation windows.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="envelope-security" numbered="true">
  <name>Approval Envelope Security</name>
    <t>
      <strong>Action hash integrity:</strong> The action_hash binds
      principal approval to specific action parameters.
      Registry MUST reject any claim where recomputed
      hash does not match stored action_hash.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Double-spend prevention:</strong> Atomic step-claim
      ensures each step claimed by exactly one actor.
    </t>

    <t>
      <strong>Envelope replay prevention:</strong> approval_id is
      UUID v4 unique per envelope. Registries MUST reject
      duplicate approval_id values.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="privacy" numbered="true">
  <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
    <t>
      AIP is designed for zero-trust environments.
      No personally identifiable information (PII) is
      transmitted in Credential Tokens beyond the AID and
      delegation chain.
    </t>

    <t>
      Registries MUST NOT log or retain Credential Token or Step Execution
      Token payloads beyond validation. Relying Parties MUST NOT store tokens
      after validation.
    </t>

    <t>
      The principal_id in Principal Tokens enables
      attribution for compliance but does not inherently
      reveal principal identity to Relying Parties.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
